<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Rounded Bloge</title>
 <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2016-10-26T15:45:34+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io</id>
 
 <author>
   <name>Rounded Globe</name>
   <email>roundedglobe@gmail.com</email>
 
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>The Crisis Confronting Humanity</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/the_crisis_confronting_humanity/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-26T15:45:34+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/the_crisis_confronting_humanity</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Humanity is confronted by two great problems of learning: learning about the nature of the universe, and learning how to become civilized. We solved the first problem when we created modern science in the 17th century, but we have not yet solved the second one. This puts us into a situation of unprecedented danger. All our current global problems have arisen as a result. For, in solving the first great problem, we created modern science and technology, the astonishing intellectual success of which has bequeathed to us - to some of us, that is - unprecedented powers to act. This has led to much that is good; it has made the modern world possible. But, in making possible modern industry and agriculture, modern medicine, hygiene, travel and armaments, it has also led to global warming, population growth, destruction of natural habitats, rapid extinction of species, pollution of earth, sea and air, the lethal character of modern war, and the threat posed by the existence of nuclear armaments. All this is the outcome of solving the first great problem of learning without also solving the second one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to dealing with the crisis that faces us is to learn from our solution to the first great problem how to solve the second one. Instead of blaming science for our troubles, we need to learn from scientific progress how to make social progress towards as good a world as possible. This is an old idea. It goes back to the French Enlightenment of the 18th century. Unfortunately, the &lt;em&gt;philosophes&lt;/em&gt; of the Enlightenment, Voltaire, Diderot, Condorcet and the rest, set about putting a thoroughly botched version of this profoundly important idea into practice - and it is this botched version that was further developed in the 19th century by Mill, Marx and others, and built into academia in the early 20th century with the creation of the social sciences. The outcome is academia devoted to the pursuit of knowledge - a kind of inquiry damagingly irrational when judged from the standpoint of helping humanity make progress towards a better, wiser world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my recently published ebook &lt;a href=&quot;https://roundedglobe.com/books/61539716-6ed9-4df5-89fa-8fdd5ec80df8/Two%20Great%20Problems%20of%20Learning:%20Science%20and%20Civilization/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Great Problems of Learning: Science and Civilization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Rounded Globe, September 2016), I spell out just what the &lt;em&gt;philosophes&lt;/em&gt; of the Enlightenment got wrong, how and why this still profoundly damages academia as it exists today, and what we need to do to put things right. We need urgently, I argue, to bring about a revolution in academic inquiry world-wide so that the basic aim becomes, not just knowledge, but rather wisdom - wisdom being the capacity and the active endeavour to realize what is of value in life for oneself and others, wisdom thus including knowledge and technological know-how, but much else besides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already my ebook has received a review - by Richard Vytniorgu in &lt;a href=&quot;http://metapsychology.mentalhelp.net/poc/view_doc.php?type=book&amp;amp;id=7746&amp;amp;cn=394&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metapsychology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; . Vytniorgu commends me for my “clarion call to a particular re-structuring of academia” but then criticizes me severely for arguing that academia should devote itself to helping humanity learn how to make progress towards a civilized world. He declares that I believe in “the possibility of cosmic perfectibility through rational human means”. He says that what I advocate “sets up impersonal concepts such as ‘civilization’ and ‘wisdom’ as a common good (or idol) to which actual individuals are liable to be sacrificed - sacrificed because of an Enlightenment belief in the possibility of such concepts’ perfectibility”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am horrified. I can find none of this in my book, and much that stands in stark opposition to it. In the book I first indicate what I take civilization to be when I say:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One could surely say, entirely uncontroversially, that absolutely minimal requirements for civilization, for global wisdom or enlightenment, are: (1) people do not periodically slaughter each other in their millions; (2) people are not politically enslaved by brutal dictatorships; (3) millions do not live in extreme poverty while millions of others live in comparative wealth; (4) the human world shows some respect for other forms of life on the planet and does not indiscriminately exterminate other species; and (5) the way of life is sustainable in the long term. Our world, despite all its scientific, technological and intellectual sophistication, satisfies none of these five elementary requirements for civilization.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to me very odd to say that, in advocating that we should try to do something about these ills that beset our world I am, by implication, advocating that individuals be sacrificed - sacrificed essentially to alleviate human suffering! This criticism seems especially unfounded given that I explicitly &lt;em&gt;criticize&lt;/em&gt; far left and far right political programmes of the past that have indeed sacrificed individuals for a distant goal. More to the point, what I argue for in my ebook is in part designed specifically to &lt;em&gt;prevent&lt;/em&gt; people being sacrificed for the attainment of a distant political goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his review, Vytniorgu ignores what is perhaps the central theme of the book: what it was precisely that the &lt;em&gt;philosophes&lt;/em&gt; got wrong, and what we need to do to put matters right. In seeking to learn from scientific progress how to achieve social progress, they (1) failed to capture correctly the progress-achieving methods of science, and (2) failed to apply these methods properly to the task of making social progress towards an enlightened world. The &lt;em&gt;philosophes&lt;/em&gt; thought, as everyone today still thinks today, that (1) the basic intellectual aim of science is truth, the basic method being that theories should be accepted on the basis of evidence, &lt;em&gt;no substantial thesis about the world being accepted permanently as a part of scientific knowledge independently of evidence&lt;/em&gt;. But this is false. Physicists only ever accept &lt;em&gt;unified&lt;/em&gt; theories even though endlessly many empirically more successful disunified rivals can always be concocted - rivals that are ignored precisely because they are disunified. This means physics accepts implicitly that the universe is such that all disunified theories are false. Science accepts that some kind of unified pattern of physical law runs through all phenomena. The basic aim of science is not truth per se; it is rather truth &lt;em&gt;presupposed to be unified&lt;/em&gt;. Precisely because this aim is profoundly problematic, it needs to be made explicit within the context of physics so that it can be critically assessed, so that alternatives can be developed and assessed, in an attempt to improve the specific aim that is pursued. We need a new conception of science - &lt;em&gt;aim-oriented empiricism&lt;/em&gt; - which sees science as making a hierarchy of metaphysical assumptions about the nature of the universe, these assumptions becoming less substantial and problematic as we go up the hierarchy. In this way we create a framework of relatively unproblematic assumptions and associated methods, high up in the hierarchy, within which much more problematic assumptions and associated methods, low down in the hierarchy, can be improved as our scientific knowledge improves. There is something like positive feedback between improving scientific knowledge, and improving aims and methods - improving knowledge about how to improve knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Failing to get the progress-achieving methods of science into sharp focus was the less serious of the &lt;em&gt;philosophes’s&lt;/em&gt; blunders. Far, far more serious, was the monumental blunder they made in &lt;em&gt;applying&lt;/em&gt; these methods. Granted that the basic idea is to learn from scientific progress how to achieve social progress towards an enlightened world, they ought to have applied appropriately generalized, progress-achieving methods of science directly to social life. Instead, disastrously, the &lt;em&gt;philosophes&lt;/em&gt; applied scientific method to the task of improving &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; about social life, to creating and developing the &lt;em&gt;social sciences&lt;/em&gt;. Instead of helping us learn how to become a bit wiser and more enlightened, the &lt;em&gt;philosophes&lt;/em&gt; sought to help us acquire &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; of social phenomena. This botched version of the profound Enlightenment idea was then developed further throughout the 19th century, and built into academia in the early 20th century with the creation of academic disciplines of anthropology, economics, sociology, psychology, political science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For over two centuries, we have put into practice a seriously botched version of the magnificent Enlightenment idea. It is long past time to correct these ancient blunders and put the Enlightenment idea properly into practice. This involves, first, getting clearly into focus the progress-achieving methods of science, generalizing them so that they become fruitfully applicable, potentially, to any worthwhile human endeavour with problematic aims, and then applying them, not to social &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt;, but to social &lt;em&gt;life&lt;/em&gt; - to government, industry, agriculture, finance, law, the media, international relations, personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not just in science that aims are problematic. This is the case in life too. Our aims at the personal, social, institutional, national and global levels are often profoundly problematic. Above all, the aim of making social progress towards a wiser, more civilized, more enlightened world is inherently and profoundly problematic, for all sorts of reasons. If we are to make real progress towards a world a little more civilized than the one we live in at present, it is essential that we learn to do, in social life, what science does - even though in the case of science this is at present obscured by the official conception of science of standard empiricism. We need to represent problematic aims in the form of a hierarchy, aims becoming less specific and problematic as we go up the hierarchy. As a result, we create a framework of relatively unproblematic aims and associated methods, high up in the hierarchy, within which much more specific and problematic aims and associated methods, low down in the hierarchy, can be progressively improved as we act, as we live, in the light of discussion and what we experience, what we suffer and enjoy, as a result of what we do. As a result of putting this &lt;em&gt;aim-oriented rationalistic&lt;/em&gt; methodology into practice in life (generalized from science), it becomes possible for us to learn how to develop and assess rival policies, political programmes, proposals for action, philosophies of life, somewhat as theories are developed and assessed in science. There is, in particular, the possibility that people with conflicting aims and ideals can learn how to resolve conflicts cooperatively within the framework of aim-oriented rationality, the different levels making it possible to distinguish where there is agreement (at the upper levels of the hierarchy) from where there is disagreement (at the lower levels). The fundamental idea would be to help people discover how to resolve problems and conflicts in increasingly cooperatively rational ways, to the extent that this is feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What, then, of Vytniorgu’s charge that I am in favour of sacrificing individuals for the perfectibility of the concepts ‘wisdom’ and ‘civilization’? One should note that this charge, if correct, makes me, in a sense, worse even than such monsters as Hitler, Stalin and Mao-Tse-tung. They sacrificed individuals - millions of individuals - for a future society they hoped to achieve; I am charged with advocating the sacrifice of individuals for nothing more than the perfectibility of &lt;em&gt;concepts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happens, a quite basic impulse behind the argument of my ebook is to counteract the horrors of Hitler and company - and the legacy they have left us. Nowadays, anyone who suggests we should take seriously the task of creating a better world is treated with grave suspicion. John Gray, in book after book, has poured scorn over the idea that progress is possible.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Vytniorgu’s criticism of my ebook is yet another expression of this popular view. It is widespread partly in reaction to the horrors produced by those in the past, whether of extreme left or right, who sought to attain a political goal by dictatorial means. But it is also widespread because so few have any awareness of what we need to do if we are to make some headway in becoming a bit more civilized without sacrificing individual people along the way - let alone millions of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we need to do? Put aim-oriented rationality into practice. This includes strengthening and spreading traditions of democracy, free speech, individual liberty, social justice, peaceful resolution of conflict. It includes transforming universities so that they put the Enlightenment idea properly into practice, thus becoming devoted to helping humanity make progress towards a better world by increasingly cooperatively rational means. And there are two further ways in which aim-oriented rationality is relevant. Utopian projects of the past have resulted in deaths, even millions of deaths, because too many have believed, with absolute, dogmatic conviction, in the attainability and desirability of some fixed political objective. Central to aim-oriented rationality is the idea that aims are all-too likely to be problematic, and in need of improvement. We are all-too likely to try to attain a goal that is unrealizable, undesirable, or both. Above all, the aim of making progress towards a good, civilized world is inherently problematic; here it is essential we implement aim-oriented rationality. Aim-oriented rationality renders the destructive fanaticism of past utopian projects quite impossible. Secondly aim-oriented rationality, applied to social endeavours, of one kind or another, is inherently social and cooperative in character. It is the very opposite of handing dictatorial power to one individual that is such a striking and horrifying feature of Hitler’s Germany and Stalin’s Soviet Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See for example J. Gray, 2004, &lt;em&gt;Heresies: Against Progress and Other Illusions&lt;/em&gt;, Granta Books, London. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>DIY Academic Publishing</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/diy-academic-publishing/"/>
   <updated>2016-07-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/diy-academic-publishing</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the old days any self-respecting group of radical intellectuals or activists worth their salt set up a printing press. Control of the means of production generated heady times, and usually also growing debt and often bankruptcy. Today, new technologies make it ridiculously easy to set up a digital press with minimal costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://roundedglobe.com/&quot;&gt;Rounded Globe&lt;/a&gt; is a scholarly e-publishing operation founded in 2014. In this post we outline our operation and vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technologies&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Our costs are as follows: web hosting, cover design, editing, coding, social media promotion. The most substantial of these costs is copy-editing (we pride ourselves on providing a service superior to most academic presses). Beyond editing and cover design, our costs do not greatly exceed those associated with running a normal website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our eBooks (as also our blog posts) are generated on the fly, with no intervention on our part, from text files stored in a Git repository. Git is a free program designed to facilitate collaboration on coding projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Git repository is a centralised store for the work that keeps track of all changes to all documents and makes them accessible and editable from anywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Texts stored in the Git repository are formatted in markdown. Markdown is a simple markup language that allows humans to easily edit raw documents and machines to easily convert the result into a plethora of formats, such as epub, mobi (kindle), and html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinguishing feature of our eBook production system is that we follow the commercial rather than the academic model. By turning our back on the pdf, the convention in academic publishing, we remove at a stroke all the costs associated with typesetting a manuscript. Pdfs are useful for embedding lots of visual information within a short text. But their adoption as the default format for books and articles is an attempt to reproduce the printed page on an electronic screen, reminiscent of the way the first printed books were designed to look like handwritten manuscripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publishing Model&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Once you have set up your Git repositories and your host website you have to decide on how to distribute your eBooks. Rounded Globe authors publish under a creative commons license that allows the work to be freely shared, which by implication means that readers download eBooks for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the surface, our decision to produce free eBooks aligns us with the open access movement. We are certainly sympathetic to the idea that the research of salaried university academics should be open to all. But Rounded Globe publishes the work of independent scholars as well as university employees, and independent scholars need to find ways to finance their research. At the heart of Rounded Globe is an experiment with a new model of scholarly production, reception, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our publishing model makes production, distribution, and revenue separate and independent activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Production&lt;/strong&gt;: If we accept a submission, and if the author agrees to publish under a creative commons license, then, without charge, we transform manuscript into eBook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distribution&lt;/strong&gt;: We share these eBooks on our website, but hold no special rights over them. The creative commons license means that copyright remains with the authors, who are free to distribute through other channels (at least two of our eBooks are also sold on Amazon), while any other site can legally host them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this model there is no place for market exchange, i.e. sales. Hence, we are unconcerned with profits, royalties, contracts, and VAT. As with the free software that runs Rounded Globe, this facilitates an uncomplicated operation and an efficient use of our time and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revenue&lt;/strong&gt;: We fund our work through donations, the most part of which are generated via a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/roundedglobe&quot;&gt;Patreon campaign&lt;/a&gt;. Patreon is a version of the crowd-funding idea tailored to artists and musicians. Dedicated fans become ‘patrons’ by committing to donate a fixed amount each time a new song/video/etc. is released. Each month Patreon distributes over $6 million in donations. Ultimately, we would like to see Patreon, or some equivalent, supporting individual scholars. At present we use it to fund Rounded Globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing we have only a handful of patrons, but their collective generosity brings us $335 each time we release a new eBook. This money is vital: it covers web hosting, cover design (outsourced) and allows us to pay a friend to do some basic social media. This still leaves editing, coding, and website maintenance. We have faith that our Patreon campaign will eventually allow Rounded Globe to (more or less) pay for itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same basic model holds also for authors. In agreeing to the creative commons license, authors commit themselves to offering their work for free on our site (they may, of course, offer it for sale elsewhere); but we place donate buttons on the download page for each eBook, and suggest a donation of $5.00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rounded Globe also incorporates a marketing strategy derived from the many thousands of new fiction writers spawned by the self-publishing revolution initiated by Amazon. Self-published authors enjoy a potentially massive market, but face an acute problem of visibility. Their most common marketing strategy is the ‘giveaway’: distributing one eBook for free in order to generate an audience for other titles. For independent scholars who want to earn some income from their writing, Rounded Globe can be regarded as a glorified giveaway, fuelling interest in other titles sold elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/bollocks.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bollocks.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Changing Academic Culture&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
The extent to which Rounded Globe can help generate an income for authors is dependent on a number of factors, most beyond our control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where we can act is on the simple question of numbers. For every 100 readers, say one donates to the author. So the more readers, the more donations (and also the more interest in other titles sold elsewhere). For this reason, Rounded Globe has a duty to our authors to use social media to promote the visibility of their eBooks. (And we are still working out how best to do this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the visibility of a title, as well as readers’ willingness to donate, is very much in the hands of the author. Today we are witnessing the emergence of a new breed of social media scholar. Eleanor Parker, one of our authors, is a good example. Eleanor &lt;a href=&quot;http://aclerkofoxford.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;blogs&lt;/a&gt; on medieval history and literature – a seemingly obscure subject, yet she has over 8,500 &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ClerkofOxford&quot;&gt;Twitter followers&lt;/a&gt;. This means that she is in a good position (far better than Rounded Globe) to promote her forthcoming title on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://roundedglobe.com/books/01164a78-c46b-4b5a-9637-1023f0abf6b6/A%20Short%20History%20of%20the%20Danish%20Conquest/&quot;&gt;Danish Conquest of England&lt;/a&gt; of 1016. But more importantly, Eleanor’s blog posts have brought a lot of people a lot of pleasure over a number of years. For such an audience the Rounded Globe donate button provides a way of expressing appreciation for more than just a single eBook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More generally, the very idea of earning an income through donations rather than a salary or royalties is dependent upon creating a new kind of cultural space within which academics engage with others. The university system supports specialists who write for other specialists, providing the wider public with little reason to engage with, let alone support academic writers. But people outside the universities are hungry for well-founded accessible scholarship, and are not without understanding of the years of research that stand behind good scholarly writing. To the extent that academics begin to write for a general audience so, we believe, new opportunities for funding research will open up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Rounded Globe provides one model of a new kind of scholarly e-publishing. Low costs and simplicity of technical operations are the keys to its survival. Both university academics and independent scholars have shown a willingness to submit manuscripts and publish under a creative commons license. As such, we have already demonstrated how easy it is to set up an ‘open access’ electronic publishing house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Rounded Globe was born from a wider vision of a different kind of academic culture, in which a substantial portion of scholarly writing is aimed at a general audience and where independent scholars have opportunities of financial remuneration. This wider vision will bear fruit only if we are able to connect with others working to similar or related goals.
We envisage Rounded Globe as a hub, with its own loose but broad community, but also connecting a variety of independent internet communities, themselves focused around the productive activities of various scholars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such communities are not markets, and their existence is premised upon a relationship of mutual trust and respect between writers and readers. They provide an alternative audience to the present disciplinary groupings of fellow specialists, for whom academics today write almost exclusively. To the extent that such communities already exist they are centred primarily around blogs, which host a series of discrete, short texts. Rounded Globe allows academic authors to take this kind of writing a step further, composing eBooks that readers can download; and we provide one way in which readers may choose to support the work of scholars.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Fire-arrows</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/fire-arrows/"/>
   <updated>2016-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/fire-arrows</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;ytvid&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&quot;video&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zTd_0FRAwOQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other Lindybeige videos &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC9pgQfOXRsp4UKrI8q0zjXQ&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Become a patron of Lindybeige videos &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/Lindybeige&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: Hartwig HKD, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/h-k-d/3125726009/&quot;&gt;‘Mars Black Sun - A4’&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Writing tablets from ancient Palmyra</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/writing-from-ancient-palmyra-2/"/>
   <updated>2016-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/writing-from-ancient-palmyra-2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Read Part I of this post &lt;a href=&quot;/writing-from-ancient-palmyra/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-in-the-world-is-socotra&quot;&gt;Where in the world is Socotra?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration left&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Untitled-2.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Untitled-2.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Desert rose (&lt;em&gt;Adenium obesium&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Situated smack in the middle of nowhere, in the Indian Ocean 250 km/155 miles east of Somalia and 340 km/210 miles from the coast of Yemen (to which it now belongs). &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socotra&quot;&gt;Socotra&lt;/a&gt; is a weirdly wonderful  island, with wide sandy beaches, karst limestone  plateaus full of caves (some as long as 7 km/4.3 miles) and mist-shrouded mountains rising to 1525m/5000’ high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;cf&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration right&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Map_copy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Map_copy.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climate is ghastly: hot, harsh, and windswept at the best of times.  The summer monsoon is far from the best  of times: from June to September, the island is so battered by fierce winds that, even today,  maritime traffic comes to a dead halt. Greeks, Arabs, Turks, Portuguese, and British mariners all tried to establish a permanent base on the island – and all gave up because it was just too horrible. A place so utterly isolated makes it, though, a happy home for a great number of strange plants and animals, many of them endemic to the island (i.e., found only here).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;cf&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a third of the species of flowering plant on the island are endemic. Not only are they unique to Socotra, but devilishly bizarre to boot.  What is one to make of such botanical oddities such as these?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/DragonsBlood.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/DragonsBlood.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Dragon blood tree (&lt;em&gt;Dracaena cinnabari&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration left&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Untitled-9.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Untitled-9.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Cucumber tree (&lt;em&gt;Dendrosicyos socotranus&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the fat Desert Rose (&lt;em&gt;adenium obesium&lt;/em&gt;), pictured at the top of the post – if that isn’t the original &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triffid&quot;&gt;Triffid&lt;/a&gt;, I don’t know what is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the cucumber tree (&lt;em&gt;Dendrosicyos socotranus&lt;/em&gt;, left) – and yes, it is related to the creeping vines of the cucumber and pickles family).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;cf&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration right&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Untitled-7.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Untitled-7.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;‘Kartab’ (&lt;em&gt;Dorstenia gigas&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the dragon blood tree (&lt;em&gt;Dracaena cinnabari&lt;/em&gt;, above centre); a tree that has no wood in it but its trunk and branches are made of a strange spongey substance so, when the tree dies, it falls to dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or the &lt;em&gt;Dorstenia gigas&lt;/em&gt;, right, otherwise known only by the Socotran name of ‘Kartab’, meaning ‘dried out, withered; stunted’ (and I can see why) – a plant that apparently doesn’t require any soil and sinks roots straight into the bare rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;cf&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t really want to talk about Socotra’s botany, fascinating though it is, but rather about one of its caves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The al-Hoq cave, on the side of a cliff about 300 m above the sea on the northeast coast of the island.  Its entrance is impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Untitled-10.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Untitled-10.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cave was first explored by Belgian speleologists less than 15 years ago.  The spelunkers found plenty of ancient pottery in the two long galleries inside (1200m/1300 yards; 800m/900 yards long), mostly containers used to collect water that dripped from the ceiling into natural basins. Much more remarkable were the grafitti found scratched into the walls of the shorter gallery by sailors and merchants who took refuge on the island when the monsoon winds unexpectedly turned against them.  As far as they can be read, some 250 inscriptions record men’s names scrawled in the scripts of ancient India (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brahmi_script&quot;&gt;Brāhmī&lt;/a&gt;, Ethiopia (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ge&#39;ez_language&quot;&gt;Guèze&lt;/a&gt;), Yemen (S. Arabian), and Bactria – all written between the 1st and 6th centuries CE.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn&quot;&gt;*&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pieces of at least 20 incense burners were found nearby, which means that the names were not meant simply to record their presence (‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://judithweingarten.blogspot.it/2013/05/i-am-hiya.html&quot;&gt;Kilroy Was Here&lt;/a&gt;’) but to call out to, or remember themselves to their gods.  One of the few longer texts makes this clear.  Written in  ancient S. Arabian, it reads: ‘Abdsiyà came here and you [the god] remained hidden from him’.  I think what poor ‘Abdsiyà is saying is: ‘This is a god-forsaken place’.  Literally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-thats-not-all-folks&quot;&gt;But that’s not all, folks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two wooden tablets and one at least is written in clear Palmyrene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted in &lt;a href=&quot;/writing-from-ancient-palmyra/&quot;&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt; of this post, the only surviving wooden tablets from Palmyra itself are those seven written by a schoolboy practicing his Greek.  And, now, we have a genuine tablet (below) written in the cursive Palmyrene script by a named adult man who had landed on Socotra and entered the Hoq cave.  The extra-large tablet (50 x 20 cm/20”x 8”)  must have been made elsewhere for there is no wood on Socotra.  We can imagine that he came with a supply of tablets to use on his journey, making notes or contracts whenever and where they were needed. Socotra was probably the last thing on his mind when he set out from Palmyra on the long, long journey to India (see the map above right; click for a larger picture).  But this is where the monsoon took him, and he left the tablet carefully placed against a stalagmite (below). We don’t know who wrote the second tablet, as it fell face down and no writing is preserved; but that, too, had been specially positioned, originally leaning against a small mound with an incense burner on top. Happily, the first tablet is legible …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Untitled-4.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Untitled-4.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and this is what it says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the month of Tammuz, day 25 of the year 569, I, Abgar, son of Abbshamay, ‘navigator’ [or ‘emissary’], have come here, to the country of Nysy; bless the god who has brought us here, and you, the man who reads this tablet, bless me [us] as well and leave the tablet in this place [where you find it].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The date is exact: the 25th day of the Semitic month of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tammuz_%28Babylonian_calendar%29&quot;&gt;Tammuz&lt;/a&gt; in the year 569 = July 258 CE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-is-this-abgar&quot;&gt;Who is this Abgar?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the odds are hugely against it, there’s a very good chance that we know something about Abgar’s family.   His father’s name Abbshamay means “servant of Heaven”, so they were probably worshippers of the Palmyran god, Balshamin (whose small, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temple_of_Baalshamin&quot;&gt;perfect temple&lt;/a&gt; was blown up by ISIS last year).  The name is only known at Palmyra in two inscriptions, both from the tomb of Nasrallât in the southwest necropolis. The inscriptions are dated to 574 (262-263 CE) et 576 (264-265 CE), and both refer to a Julius Aurelius Yedibêl, son of ‘Abdshamaya’, son of Malkû.  Given the rarity of the family name as well as the closeness in dates, it seems more than likely that Abgar and Yedibêl are related, possibly even brothers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, it is unlikely that our Abgar made it back to Palmyra.  At least, he seems not to have been buried in the family tomb. Someone so literate that he asks for a blessing from his god on the forgotten island of Socotra, and writes it in a very nice hand, would surely have left a funerary inscription for us to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if his god didn’t save him, at least those who read his plea left his tablet where he had placed it, just as he had asked them to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t ask for more than that on Socotra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;fn&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;* Now published in &lt;strong&gt;Ingo Strauch&lt;/strong&gt; [ed.]: &lt;em&gt;Foreign Sailors on Socotra : the Inscriptions and Drawings from the Cave Hoq&lt;/em&gt;, Bremen : Ute Hempen Verlag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources and Illustrations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ch. Robin, Maria Gorea, Les vestiges antiques de la grotte de Hôq (Suqutra, Yémen)
(note d’information).  In: &lt;em&gt;Comptes rendus des séances de l’Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres&lt;/em&gt;, 146e année, N. 2, 2002. pp. 409-445. The blogs &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.darkroastedblend.com/2008/09/most-alien-looking-place-on-earth.html&quot;&gt;The Dark Roasted Blend&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.paperblog.com/travel-to-socotra-island-yemen-494048/&quot;&gt;Travel to Socotra&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://socotra.info/hoq#.VzIKf-RrWxY&quot;&gt;Socotra, Dream Island&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image by &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Dragon%27s_Blood_Tree,_Socotra_Is_(12473612124).jpg&quot;&gt;Rod Waddington&lt;/a&gt;, Creative Commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Scholarship as a Vocation</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/scholarship-as-a-vocation/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/scholarship-as-a-vocation</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The modern university in 1917&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘modern university,’ as Keith Tribe has pointed out, arose by way of a misapprehension. In the 1870s and 1880s many American students attended university in Germany:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Returning graduate students brought back to the United States the ideal of the ‘modern research university’, an institution driven by academic research, its goals set by the senior professoriate, and combining the advancement of knowledge with its diffusion by teaching. Johns Hopkins was explicitly founded upon this model; Chicago later followed suit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many internationally recognized professors were employed in the nineteenth-century German universities. Nevertheless, these institutions were not prototypes of Johns Hopkins and Chicago, but state institutes essentially concerned with the vocational training of students. Max Weber in 1917, delivering the lecture now known as ‘Science as a Vocation,’ was clear that German universities needed to ‘develop in the direction of the American system.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weber’s 1917 talk has long been regarded as a classic statement of the nature of ‘intellectualization’ in the modern world. Intellectual production is equated by Weber with ‘science’ (&lt;em&gt;Wissenschaft&lt;/em&gt;), by which he means all that we might separate into the humanities, the social sciences, and the natural sciences. Science, he insists, cannot reveal ultimate values, but it does dispel traditional faith in ‘mysterious incalculable forces,’ thereby disenchanting the world. Modern science, he argues, can only be carried out within the modern university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Science today is a ‘vocation’ organized in special disciplines in the service of self-clarification and knowledge of interrelated facts… This, to be sure, is the inescapable condition of our historical situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weber presents modern science as a form of industrial activity, characterized by the division of labour, massive capital investment, and managerial supervision. His fundamental claim is that scientific advance is premised upon specialization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A really definitive and good accomplishment is today always a specialized accomplishment. And whoever lacks the capacity to put on blinders… may as well stay away from science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with all industrial activity, the logic of economic development dictates that specialized work is co-ordinated and supported within the framework of a larger organization. The modern university is a knowledge factory, established by state capital, owning the means of intellectual production, and hiring academic wage labourers who work under the supervision of departmental managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weber acknowledges that career advancement becomes a primary concern within this system, which often rewards mediocrity over merit; but he holds the ‘predominance of mediocrity’ a cost worth paying for intellectual progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The postmodern university in 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A glance at the state of universities today, nearly a century after Weber’s talk, reveals some shortcomings in his analysis. Universities are beset by a chronic shortage of funds. Changing demographics and the expansion of higher education have accentuated the problem. But it was built into the very idea of an institution that combines teaching and research. Tribe points out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The creation in the United States just over a century ago of the ‘modern university’ embodying the ideal of the teaching of students by specialized scholars was possible because of the massive fortunes made during the extraordinary period of economic expansion in the last two decades of the nineteenth century, coupled with a desire on the part of the newly rich – Johns Hopkins, Rockefeller, also Brown, Firestone and even Stetson among many others – to plough their wealth into educational foundations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such endowments were not available elsewhere, nor was this level of private donation sustainable within America. Consequently, the modern university has everywhere come to rely upon very large amounts of government funding; becoming in effect, as Weber called them in 1917, ‘state capitalist enterprises.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, the problem faced by universities today is that taxpayers and politicians are not prepared to fund the extremely expensive ideal of education to which they pay lip service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One major casualty of financial pressure is teaching, always regarded as a sort of secondary bonus component of the modern university. While more and more students have entered the universities, responsibility for teaching them is increasingly farmed out to graduates and adjuncts, leaving tenured faculty free to compete for research grants and prestigious positions. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/consciously-uncoupling-from-academia/&quot;&gt;Jillian Powers points out&lt;/a&gt;, 75% of university instruction in North American universities is now performed by contingent faculty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet this freeing up of faculty time to concentrate on research, while generating an explosion of publications, has not fostered any obvious intellectual advance. The root problem here is that, if the modern university is a factory of scientific research, it is a factory that does not produce a marketable product. Political administrators, concerned with securing results for taxpayers’ money, therefore turn to artificial measures of performance that, at least to date, have been deeply corrosive to the culture of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ranking of departments and journals, assessments of research impact, and the linking of career advancement with publication – what do these add up to beyond a recipe for a massive explosion of second-rate research? What is the real value of a hasty project, conceived with an eye on grant applications, and worked through only to the minimum level required for peer-review acceptance and consequent publication? Administrative regulation of the research factory has boosted quantity at the cost of quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation resulting from the combination of the downgrading of teaching and the administrative regulation of research is well captured by Tribe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s university teachers necessarily rely upon textbooks in their teaching rather than their own understanding of the discipline, while the formal retention of the ‘research’ culture in the mass university has massively increased the number of books and journals published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, university researchers are producing more and more publications that nobody reads because students are directed to textbooks while their peers are too busy writing grant applications and working on their next publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Artisan scholarship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of marketable product is not the only problem with Weber’s economic vision of the modern university. One may also take serious issue with his conviction that specialization is the warp and woof of intellectual advance. Certainly there is a place for specialization. But, as Weber says, specialization requires blinders, and as I have suggested &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/reflections-on-the-modern-university/&quot;&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, the disciplinary divisions of the modern university mean that these blinders are rarely if ever removed. And Weber’s idea of a disenchanted world is curiously un-self-reflexive, passing over the inherent mystery that is the self-conscious mind engaged in genuine scholarly inquiry. As Patrick Curry has &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-enchantment-of-learning/&quot;&gt;cogently argued&lt;/a&gt;, the experience of enchantment is a characteristic of genuine learning; although the modern university has done wonders in banishing this experience from its lecture halls and examination rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want here to single out another weak point in Weber’s vision of the modernization of research, namely his assumption that a single developmental trajectory applies across the board. That the natural sciences require substantial capital investment and consequent management of collectively worked resources seems obvious. But Weber also insists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This development, I am convinced, will engulf those disciplines in which the craftsman personally owns the tools, essentially the library, as is still the case to a large extent in my own field. This development corresponds entirely to what happened to the artisan of the past and it is now fully under way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether or not this made sense in 1917, it most certainly does not today. Resources such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/texts&quot;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; allow free access to just about all books and journals published before around 1905. In theory, online databases could supply open access to all later publications as well; that these libraries are closed off by paywalls is an artificial barrier to entry, providing the universities with a temporary and unjustifiable monopoly on research – temporary, because it is increasingly recognized that the move to open access is but a question of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advent of the internet turns a significant portion of academic wage-labourers into potential artisans. And this undermines the basic rationale behind Weber’s conviction that ‘the inescapable condition of our historical situation’ is that intellectual production must be ‘organized in special disciplines’ within the modern university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who are committed to life within the university may find in these reflections some clues for reform. And, clearly, fundamental reform is needed. But those called to the humanities and the social sciences, who understand their vocation in terms of scholarship as opposed to career advancement and status, might do well to consider whether they have any place in the universities at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artisan scholarship requires a financial basis, and independent scholars need to find ways to support their studies. That this is possible has been demonstrated by a number of independent scholars, one of whom has provided the core research on which this post has drawn (&lt;a href=&quot;http://keithtribe.co.uk/translation/&quot;&gt;Keith Tribe&lt;/a&gt; runs his own translation company). A loose organization of independent scholars could, in theory, secure patronage from private corporations, and even make a bid for state funding, as do other arts. But the most exciting way forward at this moment in time is surely to explore the possibilities opened up by crowd-funding initiatives. Such grass-roots support of scholarship would inevitably entail a welcome shift of audience, compelling scholars to address interested laypeople as opposed to a handful of fellow specialists. Those who regard scholarship as their vocation have been let down by the modern university but may find a solution online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bibliography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the sources linked within the text, this post has made ample use of Keith Tribe’s ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.academia.edu/7288614/Educational_Economies&quot;&gt;Educational Economies&lt;/a&gt;’, published in &lt;em&gt;Economy and Society&lt;/em&gt;, 2006, and available on Keith’s academia.edu page, and Max Weber’s ‘Wissenschaft als Beruf’, for which I used the translation by H.H. Gerth and C. Wright Mills, of which several versions can be found online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: Ekin Arabacioglu, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/ekinarabaci/3477405030/&quot;&gt;‘Cogs’&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Consciously Uncoupling from Academia</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/consciously-uncoupling-from-academia/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/consciously-uncoupling-from-academia</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the longest time I wanted to be a college professor, and if I’m going to be truly honest with myself, it was because of the movie &lt;em&gt;Dead Poets Society&lt;/em&gt;. I first saw the movie when I was young and impressionable. I thought that once I got to college, classrooms would be filled with professors like Mr. Keating—passionate teacher-scholars who wore their hearts on their sleeve and demanded personal growth from their students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I actually got to college, I learned that things were not that simple. There was a whole set of cultural and educational scripts I was supposed to have already mastered and a whole set of assumptions placed upon my body (based upon my race, class, and gender) that I wasn’t ready to accept or understand. To mask my feelings of inadequacy, I shrunk into myself. But, as an outsider at Dartmouth College, I also kept my eyes open. I learned that my social position and identity shaped how I saw the world, and also shaped how the world responded to me. In college, I fell in love with Sociology, the discipline that helped me make sense of it all. I became more curious. What were the experiences of others, how did their social location shape their opportunities and worldviews? I became fascinated with community, identity, cultural scripts, and belonging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For over a decade, the academic calendar dictated the rhythms of my life. I spent my twenties, and half of my thirties cultivating, or trying to cultivate, the manners and language of the elite academic professional sociologist. Along the way I floundered, slapped about, and found meaning in other disciplinary directions and social spaces. I also fell in love with grand theory, learned how to humbly engage with others, found ways to see patterns in social texts, and discovered I could write deeply and richly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose sociology because I wanted to master a methodologically rigorous practice to examine the social world, and I saw a career as a professor as a way to keep me nimble and allow me to explore, travel, and share what I learned. Nothing gives me more pleasure than being able to pick apart an idea as if it were a scab. I learned to love words and find a powerful sense of accomplishment in my ability to craft textured thick description. Even now as I work to craft a book, sentence by sentence, the process gives me chills. I’ve shared my work and my expertise at conferences, in workshops, with the public in a variety of ways, and, most importantly, in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m the most present when I’m teaching; I have to be. As an interdisciplinary scholar of race and ethnicity, I have to be constantly aware of how I present and engage with the lived experiences of others. While I am the expert in the room, my knowledge is also partial. I cannot know everything, nor can I truly step into the affective experience of others. This is not a confession of my intellectual or academic weakness; on the contrary, this is a powerful standpoint to teach from. I approach the interactive nature of learning humbly, and, in turn, expect my students to make mistakes, yet strive for growth and excellence. As we work together to analyze and understand important contemporary social issues, I encourage students to speak from their own experience and think of more inventive ways to share their knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With me at the helm, students learn to speak across divides, take risks that might leave them vulnerable, and, in the process we wind up building coalitions and creating supportive communities. In my classroom, strangers meet, ideas are aired, and problems are diagnosed—all while we maintain respect for each other and support for everyone’s ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the classroom was reparative. It was my contribution to a better and more just world. Nothing has given me more pleasure in life than being a small part in someone else’s journey of discovery. I learned a great deal from my students. From their eyes, I saw different pieces of the world. I also learned how to be brave. If they were willing to trust me to be a mentor and a role model, I had to live it. I could not remain silent about how the structures of higher education were preventing me from doing my best work.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher education in North America is going through serious transformations. The percentage of college students who are Hispanic, Asian/Pacific Islander, Black, and Native American has been increasing steadily while the percentage of white students declines. Unfortunately, increased enrollment and newfound visibility does not necessarily translate into a seat at the table. University administration and faculty do not reflect the demographic shifts seen in student populations. In 2013, 84 percent of full-time professors were white, and 53% white male.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; At Brandeis (where I am currently finishing up a one-year contract), 80 percent of full-time instructional faculty who report a race/ethnicity, identify as white (non-Hispanic), 8 percent as Asian, 4 percent as Hispanic, and only 1 percent as black.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; In this changing campus environment, it is not a stretch to think that sometimes our unconscious actions might lead to someone else’s discomfort, alienation, or subordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, tuitions continue to rise, but rarely do those funds trickle down to the classroom. More money is being funneled into administrative positions and away from tenure-line hires.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; The number of administrative positions has more than &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/02/06/higher-ed-administrators-growth_n_4738584.html&quot;&gt;doubled in the last 25 years&lt;/a&gt;. Rarely is this new top-heavy model successful, productive, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2013/06/18/nyu_loans_for_summer_homes_ny_times_story_about_university_pay_for_john.html&quot;&gt;beneficial&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/sites/default/server_files/files/profstaff(2).pdf&quot;&gt;students&lt;/a&gt;. To balance this bloat, funds are siphoned away from instruction. Salaries for full-time faculty are barely higher than what they were &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/04/05/opinion/sunday/the-real-reason-college-tuition-costs-so-much.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;in 1970&lt;/a&gt;, and most teaching positions are now part-time and low-paid adjunct positions. According to a 2012 report from the American Association of University Professors, contingent faculty make up over 75% of all instructional staffing. In 1975 only 25% were in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aaup.org/report/heres-news-annual-report-economic-status-profession-2012-13&quot;&gt;these positions&lt;/a&gt;. Even elite schools rely heavily on non-tenure track &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/articles/life/education/2015/10/malia_obama_college_application_process_labor_practices_at_her_top_choices.html&quot;&gt;labor&lt;/a&gt;. Being part of that 75% &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hookandeye.ca/2016/01/once-more-with-feelings.html&quot;&gt;really sucks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With few options for stable employment, early-career academics have to hustle. Wherever the job is, you go. Since 2011, I’ve lived in three different states; this is not uncommon. &lt;a href=&quot;http://ecologybits.com/index.php/2016/03/23/i-am-unwilling-to-relocate-again-and-it-will-probably-cost-me-my-academic-career/&quot;&gt;Multiple moves&lt;/a&gt; are now the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/advice/2016/04/15/difficulties-constantly-having-move-academic-essay,&quot;&gt;norm in academia&lt;/a&gt;, and, unfortunately, they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Vic_Catano/publication/232565678_Occupational_Stress_in_Canadian_Universities_A_National_Survey/links/5548bca40cf27c50006680a1.pdf&quot;&gt;take their toll&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep going, I spent more time in isolation, struggling to balance the pieces of this career that brought me joy with the pieces that academia rewards. I kept shedding the enriching parts of life that sustain me and connect me to others. In turn, my work and my spirit began to suffer. I felt isolated and alone, full of shame and regret that the reality of my circumstance was of my own making, but I am a sociologist, and I know the relationship between troubles and issues (Mills 1967:395; Mills 1959:8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many professors are satisfied with their jobs and are emotionally committed to their universities, recent studies reveal that professors are under &lt;a href=&quot;http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/str/17/3/232/&quot;&gt;extreme levels of stress&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2016/01/28/hashtag-unites-adjuncts-and-tenure-line-professors-over-work-life-balance-and-other&quot;&gt;We’re all feeling&lt;/a&gt; the crunch of the corporate university. Unrealistic research expectations and metrics for “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2011/05/10/texas_faculty_and_president_criticize_regents_measurement_of_professors&quot;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt;,” challenges to academic &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2011/04/062/how_should_college_professors_respond_to_allegations_of_research_misconduct_in_the_age_of_the_internet&quot;&gt;freedom and expertise&lt;/a&gt;, lack of job security, the reliance on adjunct labor, the dismantling of tenure,&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; the emerging student-as-customer model, and the increasingly administrative nature of academic work and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2011/02/02/aaup_blasts_rensselaer_polytechnic_institute_for_icing_shared_governance&quot;&gt;shrinking role professors and faculty&lt;/a&gt; have in the management of the institutions they work in has made this a very &lt;a href=&quot;https://profkrampus.wordpress.com/2016/04/01/why-academia-should-be-burnt-to-the-ground-personal-anecdotes/&quot;&gt;hostile environment&lt;/a&gt; in which to think and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/humansofnewyork/posts/1224039557670142&quot;&gt;share information&lt;/a&gt;. Collectively, we are so stressed and slammed for time that we no longer &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.straitstimes.com/opinion/prof-no-one-is-reading-you&quot;&gt;read the work of our peers&lt;/a&gt;. Academic journal articles, heavy with jargon, collect virtual dust behind &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/articles/life/education/2014/07/the_easy_way_to_fix_peer_review_require_submitters_to_review_first.html&quot;&gt;expensive paywalls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Committed teachers and scholars are walking away, and they’re not doing it silently.&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://marginalia.lareviewofbooks.org/silence-wont-protect-you/&quot;&gt;Silence will not pave&lt;/a&gt; the way for someone else, or make the environment more just. This is why I write this, because, like Audre Lorde, I believe that “what is most important to me must be spoken, made verbal, and shared, even at the risk of having it bruised or misunderstood” (1978). I add my voice to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2013/10/24/quitting_academic_jobs_professor_zachary_ernst_and_other_leaving_tenure.html&quot;&gt;choir of voices&lt;/a&gt;. I am consciously uncoupling from Academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I reconcile this change in identity, I keep thinking about the Introduction to Ann Cvetkovish’s book, &lt;em&gt;Depression: a Public Feeling&lt;/em&gt;. In it, she uses memoir to understand how the expectations and culture of higher education contributed to and colored her own struggles with anxiety and depression. Living through this, and now safely tenured, she wonders: “what kind of projects might emerge out of these conditions”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the real question is where else will scholarship come from, and what forms will it take when all the talent leaves and floods different markets? We’ve seen the rise and popularity of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2015-06-04/help-wanted-black-belts-in-data&quot;&gt;data scientist&lt;/a&gt;. Is the &lt;em&gt;people scientist&lt;/em&gt; right behind? Can we envision a productive future for the humanities and social sciences that happens to grow out of the systemic failure of higher education?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the driving force that shapes my life and brought me to higher education in the first place, to quote Herbert Blumer, has been to “lift the veils that cover… group life.” The veils are lifted, he continues, “by digging deep…through careful study” (1969). Shaped by intersectional feminism, cultural studies, and critical theory, &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; method of choice is participant observation and ethnography, and I have mainly been lifting veils in the classroom and in my academic writing. However, students and other academics are not the only people who can benefit from a more accurate understanding of social life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our increasingly fractured world, the humanist and social scientist must be drafted into service. Their skills and expertise are desperately needed. We must be willing to leave the gilded cage and apply our scholarship and the valuable work of our colleagues all in the pursuit of a better future. In industry, government, think tanks, policy centers, and on the front lines of social movements we can serve society directly. As outsiders in these spaces, with keen theoretical foundations and strong methodological training, we see things others overlooked. We offer new strategies based on alternative frameworks, and use our experience to envision and enact change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how we make knowledge accessible and create a new generation of nimble public intellectuals. I draw inspiration and strength from a diverse and passionate group of scholars, colleagues, mentors, and friends. For example, after leading a teach-in on Duke University’s campus, sociologist Eduardo Bonilla-Silva saw a new opportunity. “Another sociology is indeed possible,” he shared on Facebook. “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/eduardo.bonillasilva.7/posts/10154180324034668&quot;&gt;But we must change how we do things. We must appreciate that our intellectual work must be rigorous, but accessible…Knowledge must be democratic, public, accessible, open, critical, and disseminated in a faster way.&lt;/a&gt;” Change means growth, and growth can be powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As applied humanists and people scientists, we extend the reach of our knowledge into areas desperate for our expertise. We can forge connections, continue to learn, create change, and sleep soundly knowing that our bills are getting paid. Yes, there is anxiety and challenges here too. Working outside the academy means directing our skills and expertise towards practical outcomes and useful interventions. When working towards something achievable, you have to take budgetary constraints, political climates, short timetables and strict deadlines into consideration. This requires a level of compromise and an acceptance that the outcomes based on our work will always be imperfect. I, personally, will not lose sleep over this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I walk away, to paraphrase another of my favorite thinkers, “in my flesh, and in the images of my work,” I will embody the broad and inclusive definition of scholarship (Anzaldúa 2007:102). Yes, there will be a learning curve, and yes, this will require me to first watch and then listen before contributing. It also requires me to be brave and less timid. I’ve let academia wear me down. But, I didn’t get a PhD so I could signal a douchey form of elite smartness; I saw it as a career path that would constantly challenge me. My dissertation advisor once said that a PhD is like a fishing license. With it, you are now authorized to &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; sociology. For me, it’s time to check out other ponds, and catch some larger fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Evelyn Nakano Glenn, “Whose Public Sociology? The Subaltern Speaks, but Who Is Listening? In Public Sociology, University of California Press. 2007&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; U.S. Department of Education, National Center for Education Statistics. (2015). The Condition of Education 2015 (NCES 2015-144), &lt;a href=&quot;https://nces.ed.gov/programs/coe/indicator_cuf.asp&quot;&gt;Characteristics of Postsecondary Faculty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brandeis.edu/about/facts/faculty.html&quot;&gt;This evaluation&lt;/a&gt; is limited to the full-time instructional faculty who specified a racial/ethnic group membership (90% of all full-time faculty).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; The Fall of the Faculty: The Rise of the All-Administrative University and Why it Matters, by Benjamin Ginsberg and David Bernstein. 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; The Faculty Lounges: And Other Reasons Why You Won’t Get the College Education you Pay For, by Naomi Schaefer Riley. 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; See, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doctorouttahere.wordpress.com/2012/07/26/leaving-academia-a-letter-of-explanation/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/pieces/being-failed-professor-lessons-margins-and-undercommons&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/views/2016/04/21/adjunct-explains-why-she-has-quit-her-job-essay&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2013/06/18/nyu_loans_for_summer_homes_ny_times_story_about_university_pay_for_john.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: simpleinsomnia, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/simpleinsomnia/14520685739/&quot;&gt;‘Men inspecting a train wreck 3’&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Isles and Europe</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-isles-and-europe/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-isles-and-europe</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the wake of EU referendum result, Wilhelm Levison’s &lt;em&gt;England and the Continent in the Eighth Century&lt;/em&gt; (1946) keeps coming to mind. In the preface to that work, he wrote: ‘May these pages, in their small way, contribute to join again broken links.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenges for Europe then – in 1943 when he delivered the Ford Lectures in Oxford, in 1945 when he wrote the preface to their published text – were hopefully greater than they are now. Levison’s hopes for what he could achieve by talking about England and the continent were certainly modest. He did not invoke a golden age of interactions between the Anglo-Saxon and Frankish worlds as an unrealistic utopian counter to war. What he showed was how mundane trade networks, the migration of ideas and intellectuals, and diplomatic relations between political centres, all played crucial roles in redefining Western Europe in its Late Antiquity. He saw the early flow of ideas from the continent to the English, not least with Pope Gregory the Great’s missionaries to Kent late in the sixth century, paving the way generations later for the great missionaries from England (St Willibrord [d. 739], St Boniface [d. 754]) whose activities laid the foundations for Christian culture in the Netherlands and Germany. Cross-Channel interactions were highly productive in the long term. Levison concluded, amongst other things, by quoting &lt;a href=&quot;https://merovingianworld.wordpress.com/2016/01/19/isidore-burckhardt-and-brown-guest-blog-by-david-ganz/&quot;&gt;Jacob Burkhardt&lt;/a&gt;: ‘A truly rich nation becomes rich by accepting much from others and developing it’.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Levison, this sense of co-operation was important, as he found himself in England because he had been forced to flee Nazi Germany in 1939. He died in 1947 shortly after the publication of &lt;em&gt;England and the Continent&lt;/em&gt; when only the first seeds of renewed peace had been sown. In early medieval studies, the idea of seeing networks and occasional connections cutting productively across national boundaries remained strong. And not just for understanding the Anglo-Saxons, as the publication of &lt;a href=&quot;https://he.palgrave.com/page/detail/The-Irish-in-Early-Medieval-Europe/?K=9781137430595&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Irish in Early Medieval Europe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago reminds us. Behind any story told about nations and peoples are stories about people who cross boundaries to achieve things. And maybe, again in future, histories about connections will be able to contribute to joining links seemingly broken in recent times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Further Reading&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matthias Becher &amp;amp; Yitzhak Hen (eds.), Wilhelm Levison (1876-1947) (Siegburg, 2010).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roy Flechner &amp;amp; Sven Meeder (eds.), The Irish in Early Medieval Europe: Identity, Culture and Religion (London, 2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilhelm Levison, England and the Continent in the Eighth Century (Oxford, 1946).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Palmer, Anglo-Saxons in a Frankish World 690-900 (Turnhout, 2009).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joanna Story, Carolingian Connections: Anglo-Saxon England and Carolingian Francia, c. 750-870 (Aldershot, 2003).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; ‘Ein wahrhaft reiches Volk wird dadurch reich, daß es von anderen vieles übernimmt und weiterbildet’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: Patrick Marioné, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/p_marione/11764053065/&quot;&gt;‘Marty, stop to play with that animal ! Come eat your snack’&lt;/a&gt;, St Boniface, Bruxelles. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A letter to friends who voted Leave</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/a-letter-to-friends-who-voted-leave/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/a-letter-to-friends-who-voted-leave</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last few days I’ve seen Leave voters on Facebook posting in annoyance that Remain voters are not sitting in quiet acceptance of Friday’s result. Apparently it’s an outrage to democracy that those of us who voted differently have the nerve to be upset about the result and to express ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this bemusing (did y’all get a different Ladybird book of democracy to me?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Referendums are always divisive. It’s not like a General Election where, after initial disappointment, it’s time to move on because there will always be another chance in five years. They are for keeps. It is perfectly reasonable to expect the losing side to be hurt and it should go without saying that the losing side deserve time to express their disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a lot of expectation from Leave voters that it’s now up to those of us on the Remain side to kiss and makeup. You feel righteous and victorious, but have forgotten to be humble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you won, but your margin of victory was small: backed by only 26.7% of the UK’s total population (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-36605899&quot;&gt;65,100,000&lt;/a&gt;) and 37.4% of registered voters (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.electoralcommission.org.uk/i-am-a/journalist/electoral-commission-media-centre/news-releases-referendums/provisional-electorate-figures-published-ahead-of-the-eu-referendum&quot;&gt;46,499,537&lt;/a&gt;). A victory, yes, but not a resounding endorsement of one of the most significant changes to the UK in a century. If you are serious about healing the divisions your vote has wrought then learn to be magnanimous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I heard the news on Friday morning (and when I saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/24/brexit-leader-said-victory-came-without-a-bullet-being-fired-he-seems-to-have-forgotten-jo-cox/&quot;&gt;Farage crowing about ‘no shots fired’&lt;/a&gt; and that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ThatSabineGirl/status/746370534036881408?lang=en-gb&quot;&gt;Sun had put a member of Combat 18 on the front page&lt;/a&gt;) I felt like I had lost my country. I understand that – for different reasons – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/uk/2016/06/how-think-about-eu-result-if-you-voted-remain&quot;&gt;this is exactly how many Leave voters have felt for years&lt;/a&gt;. Yet I suspect this sense of disillusionment crept in and developed slowly. For Remain voters it was in the blink of an eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put yourself in our shoes and imagine waking up one morning to discover that everything you thought you knew had been irreversibly destroyed. Wouldn’t you be upset if part of your identity, your sense of place and belonging were involuntarily torn away from you in the flash of a BBC bulletin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Leave campaign &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2016/06/22/the-brexit-debate-has-made-britain-more-racist/&quot;&gt;has legitimised&lt;/a&gt; the spread of division and &lt;a href=&quot;http://indy100.independent.co.uk/article/sadiq-khan-called-out-the-leave-campaigns-project-hate-and-got-the-biggest-cheer-of-the-bbc-eu-debate--ZkM5b5Hc4W&quot;&gt;hate&lt;/a&gt;. I know that the vast majority of Leave voters are not xenophobes and of course you are not personally responsible for the recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2016/06/26/spate-of-racist-attacks-blamed-on-brexit-vote/&quot;&gt;post-referendum spree of racist abuse&lt;/a&gt;, but (to paraphrase &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.spectator.co.uk/2016/06/a-day-of-infamy/&quot;&gt;Alex Massie’s wonderful Spectator column&lt;/a&gt; on the murder of Jo Cox) I haven’t seen any evidence you are doing much to stop it either. Stop laughing your ass off as you repost &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-3660263/Day-Brexit-went-viral-Thomas-Tank-Engine-blocked-bricked-Channel-Tunnel-joker-designs-logo-Scotlond.html&quot;&gt;Thomas the Tank engine and NWA themed Leave memes&lt;/a&gt; and go and do something to combat the hate, because right now your stance makes you complicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are scared. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/higher-education-network/2015/may/13/eu-science-funding-the-uk-cannot-afford-to-lose-out-on-this-pot-of-money&quot;&gt;The loss&lt;/a&gt; of EU money &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raeng.org.uk/publications/responses/joint-national-academies-submission&quot;&gt;for Higher Education&lt;/a&gt; and the potential loss of EU students is going to be hugely damaging for our universities. The construction sector – already facing negative growth – &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/live/2016/jun/27/pound-shares-markets-brexit-crisis-osborne-lew-business-live?page=with:block-57711306e4b0be24d34f64f2#block-57711306e4b0be24d34f64f2&quot;&gt;is in freefall&lt;/a&gt;. Research, innovation and business investment are going to take a beating as we suffer a brain drain, a financial drain and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/recession-forecast-to-follow-brexit-vote-rc8bj3cmd&quot;&gt;growth killing paralysis that two years of uncertainty introduces&lt;/a&gt;. If you voted Leave then have the decency to understand that people are going to lose their jobs as a result of your choice (this is personal to me, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dougsarchaeology.wordpress.com/2016/06/20/what-brexit-or-exit-will-mean-for-archaeology-really-all-of-the-uk/&quot;&gt;my own sector is likely in dire trouble&lt;/a&gt;). Understand that people are scared that their hopes and dreams for the future are in ashes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaders of the campaign you supported are, to all intents and purposes, hiding (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/politics/live/2016/jun/27/brexit-live-george-osborne-economy-corbyn-shadow-cabinet?page=with:block-57711942e4b0f4303810a0cf#block-57711942e4b0f4303810a0cf&quot;&gt;the Leave website is already removing many of its documents and promises&lt;/a&gt;). In their absence it falls on you to make this work. You expressed your anger at the ballot box, now take responsibility. Maybe something good can come out of this and perhaps the future isn’t as bleak as I (and many others) fear. Prove us wrong. Prove to us that this is more than simply “&lt;a href=&quot;http://stumblingandmumbling.typepad.com/stumbling_and_mumbling/2016/06/vote-remain-a-simple-decision.html&quot;&gt;a mandate for Farage and the inward-looking, reactionary mean-spirited philistinism he embodies&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will take a long time for what remains of this country to heal, and even then the scars will remain. Your Leave vote doesn’t change that we are friends and acquaintances (and I will never reduce you to solely your vote on this issue), but I’m finding it hard to forgive you for who you chose to stand with.
If you want metaphorical make-up sex then you are going to have to start the heavy lifting first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right, I’m going to listen the new Swans album really bloody loud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ytvid&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&quot;video&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ka_hKb7dSiY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: cogito ergo imago, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/37244380@N00/27264765303/&quot;&gt;‘Pieces In Our Time’&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Writing tablets from ancient Palmyra</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/writing-from-ancient-palmyra/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/writing-from-ancient-palmyra</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Palmyra has been in the news of late due to the destruction wrought by Islamic State. In this post Judith Weingarten takes us back to a bar in happier days…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One story is good, till another is told&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two men, by the names of Aesop and Babrius, and a schoolboy walked into a wine bar in ancient Palmyra. Aesop ordered three cups of date-palm wine and toasted his companions, telling a fable about an eagle and a jackdaw (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aesopfables.com/cgi/aesop1.cgi?2&amp;amp;TheEagleandtheJackdaw&quot;&gt;Aesop 2&lt;/a&gt;).  Babrius laughs, buys another round of wine, and says, “Aesop, best of fabulists, truly you are an eagle but I’ll show you I’m no daw.” With barely a pause, he renders Aesop’s prose into verse (Babrius 137):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An eagle with his talons lifted a sleek lamb from the flock
and carried it off to give to his young ones for a meal.
A jackdaw started to do the same,
swooped down and fastened on the back of a lamb. 
Unable to lift the lamb, his claws became entangled in its fleece, 
there boys caught him and clipped his wings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration smallimg left&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/jw1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jw1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Zebida son of Taimamed holding polyptych tied
 up by a strap and a wide tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The schoolboy - probably similar in age and appearance to Zebida son of Taimamed, the scholarly child whose portrait is on the left - was eagerly writing down Babrius’ words on a tablet covered with wax.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, he piped up with the moral of the story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pay a just penalty for my folly, he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why did I, who am only a jackdaw,&lt;br /&gt;
try to imitate the eagle?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all that he said was written in Greek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From Palmyra to Leiden&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration smallimg right&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/jw2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jw2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here (below right) is the actual wax tablet that the schoolboy scribbled on.  His writing looks as if he had inbibed a little too much wine: most lines are not straight, spacing is irregular and there are spelling errors in his Greek.  But, in truth, given that his own language was Palmyrene and he was just learning Greek, the result isn’t really bad at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is amazing, however, is that this tablet still exists: in fact, seven wax tablets (probably once bound together as a polyptych - a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diptych&quot;&gt;diptych&lt;/a&gt; + five) - were bought by a Dutch naval officer, Mr H. van Assendelft de Coningh, in Palmyra in 1881 (“During my brief visit to Palmyra I acquired these wooden tablets”).  What amazing luck: these are the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; inscribed tablets known to have come from ancient Palmyra. After Van Assendelft de Coningh’s death, his brother donated the tablets to the Leiden University library which gave them the name of &lt;em&gt;Tabulae ceratae Assendelftianae&lt;/em&gt; in honour of the family.  The tablets are still to be found in that library and, even better, they can now be &lt;a href=&quot;https://socrates.leidenuniv.nl/R/-?func=dbin-jump-full&amp;amp;object_id=4433833&quot;&gt;viewed online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When is a fable not a fable?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1893, Leiden professor Dirk Hesseling published the tablets.  He had discovered “after great effort and repeated squinting” that they contained 13 fables by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babrius&quot;&gt;Babrius&lt;/a&gt;, a Greek-speaking Roman poet living in Syria in the second half of the first century CE.  Babrius is the author of almost 200 fables that were traditionally attributed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aesop&quot;&gt;Aesop&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, Babrius himself tells us in his book’s introduction that he was the first to put Aesopic prose into verse:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You may learn and fully understand from wise old Aesop, who has told us fables in the free manner of prose.  And now I shall adorn each of these fables with the flowers of my own Muse.  I shall set before you a poetical honeycomb, as it were, dripping with sweetness….&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration smallimg left&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/jw3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jw3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Unnamed boy holding stylus and polyptych
with Greek inscription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In antiquity, the fables of Babrius were commonly used as an easy reader for young children when they were first learning to speak and write Greek.  “Let them learn,” &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quintilian&quot;&gt;Quintilian&lt;/a&gt; says (I,9,1) “first to tell the fables orally in clear, unpretentious language, then to write them out with the same simplicity of style….”   Such stories featuring anthropomorphised animals and containing moralistic wisdom were a good way to teach Greek to school children.  The somewhat older lad pictured (left) is proud of his Greek: his open stack of waxed tablets displays the last five letters of the Greek alphabet – but written in Palmyrene (Aramaic) order, from right to left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The empire was multilingual, and learning Greek as a second language was a necessity in the eastern empire - and nowhere more so than in Palmyra, especially for its merchants who travelled far and wide, often to the very edges of the known world. The many monumental inscriptions of the city carved on its pillars and walls, reflect their cosmopolitan ways: many hundreds are bilingual, written in both Palmyrene and Greek.  The ability to use Aramaic and Greek alphabets seems not to have been uncommon at Palmyra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration smallimg right&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/jw4.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/jw4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why our Palmyran schoolboys started learning the Greek alphabet and language at a young age, perhaps soon after having learnt to read and write the entirely different Palmyrene (Aramaic) script.  All seven &lt;em&gt;Tabulae ceratae Assendelftianae&lt;/em&gt; were written by a single schoolboy who lived in the city in the early third century CE (as can be determined from the form of his letters). On some tablets, he  practiced his hand in both book-script - printing his letters - and cursive - joining them up (as bottom right).  It’s very likely that his teacher was dictating the fables while the boy wrote them down as he thought he heard them - with all the errors and smudges, deletions and guesswork that you would expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something very tender in the thought that we have retrieved the halting efforts of a young Palmyran in the early stages of learning the Greek language; we can almost picture him as he hurried to school on the streets of Palmyra with wax tablets tied by strings. But, in all truth, it is disappointing, too, that the surviving texts on these tablets are only the rather banal fables of Babrius - already known to us from many sources throughout the Roman Empire.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; Can you imagine if instead they had recorded epic battles in the wars against Sasanian Persia, or hymns to the gods of Palmyra, or records of a merchant’s far-away travels?  Alas, that was not to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet there is one more inscribed wooden tablet written by a Palmyran, and it only came to light a dozen or so years ago.  It was found far from the city, on the distant and dangerous route that merchants took on their way to India.  This tablet deserves to be better known.  I’ll tell you about it in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;cf&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read Part II of this post &lt;a href=&quot;/writing-from-ancient-palmyra-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Wax tablets – small wooden boards covered in a layer of wax were used throughout Antiquity and the Middle Ages. The wax surface used to write on could be easily wiped clean and reused.  It allowed erasure and reuse of the writing surface, making them suitable for use at schools, taking notes, etc. Tablets are very rarely found with wax layer and writing intact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; Recently cleaned and restored by Karin Scheper of the Leiden Univ. Library: &lt;em&gt;Over the years fungus had grown on the wax layers, rendering the texts illegible. Scheper removed the fungus by carefully rolling a cotton swab, saturated with demineralised water and ethanol, over the wax layer. She then cut and folded new cassettes out of cardboard, allowing the tablets to ‘breathe’, eliminating the breeding conditions for fungi&lt;/em&gt;. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/NINO.Leiden/posts/1038808922858991:0&quot;&gt;Greek Wax Tablets from Palmyra Restored&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; In all fairness, though the tales are known elsewhere in prose, four of the thirteen fables (Babrius 136-9) on these tablets are nowhere else preserved in verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was first published on Judith’s website, &lt;a href=&quot;http://judithweingarten.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;Zenobia: Empress of the East&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main Sources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D. C. Hesseling, “On Waxen Tablets with Fables of Babrius (Tabulae Ceratae Assendelftianae)”, JHS Vol. 13 (1892 - 1893), 293-314.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B.E. Perry, Babrius and Phaedrus, Loeb Classical Library, 1965.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Łukasz Sokołowski, “WRITING ATTRIBUTES IN ICONOGRAPHY OF THE PALMYRENE FUNERARY STELA AND THE LOCAL SOCIAL IDENTITIES EXPRESSED,” 18th CIAC: Centro y periferia en el mundo clásico/Centre and periphery in the ancient world, Mérida 2015, 1237-1240.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Idem, “Portraying Literacy of Palmyra, 2014” Etudes et Travaux XXVII, 2014,376-403.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greek Wax Tablets from Palmyra Restored, NINO 28 February 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illustrations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top left: Zebida son of Taimamed holding polyptych and a wide tablet. Palmyra,Palmyra Museum, inv. no. 1973/7065. Photo credit: Sokołowski 2014, Fig. 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2nd left: Wax tablet from Palmyra. Photo credit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://catalogue.leidenuniv.nl/primo_library/libweb/action/dlDisplay.do?vid=UBL_V1&amp;amp;search_scope=All_Content&amp;amp;docId=UBL_LMS003766881&amp;amp;fn=permalink&quot;&gt;Tabulae ceratae graecae quae vocantur Assendelftianae&lt;/a&gt;, Leiden University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3rd left: Unnamed boy holding stylus and polyptych with Greek inscription. Late 2nd-early 3rd century CE. Photo credit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://cartelen.louvre.fr/cartelen/visite?srv=car_not_frame&amp;amp;idNotice=21039&amp;amp;langue=en&quot;&gt;Louvre Museum, inv. no. AO 18174&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower left: Wax tablet from Palmyra. Photo credit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://catalogue.leidenuniv.nl/primo_library/libweb/action/dlDisplay.do?vid=UBL_V1&amp;amp;search_scope=All_Content&amp;amp;docId=UBL_LMS003766881&amp;amp;fn=permalink&quot;&gt;Tabulae ceratae graecae quae vocantur Assendelftianae&lt;/a&gt;, Leiden University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image Filip Gierlinski, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/filskifoto/5547410778&quot;&gt;‘Palmyra Views’&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Neoliberal University</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/reflections-on-the-modern-university/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/reflections-on-the-modern-university</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Simon J. Cook, intellectual historian, on the relationship between neoclassical economics, disciplinary autonomy, and the moden English university system.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been studying English intellectual history for nearly three decades, focusing on the years between 1865 and 1925. At the beginning of this period intellectual life in England took place largely outside the universities; by the end of it the modern university had emerged, replete with its professional journals and division of faculties, and has claimed a monopoly over serious scholarship ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet a decade ago I resolved to pursue my own research as an independent scholar, without any university affiliation. In this post I offer some reflections on how my work has shaped my attitude toward the modern university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A child of Thatcher, my early research explored the origins of neoclassical economics. Specifically, I looked at the reformation of classical economics at the hands of Alfred Marshall, the founder of modern university economics. Marshall established economics as an independent discipline in Cambridge in 1903, but his intellectual innovations occurred in the early 1870s, when political economy formed part of the ‘moral sciences’ faculty and his university was in the midst of wholesale overhaul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oxford and Cambridge are medieval institutions, but the Elizabethan settlement had established them as bastions of the English Reformation. The first part of the nineteenth century saw sustained agitation from religious dissenters to end the Anglican monopoly and ‘nationalize’ the ancient universities. By the 1870s, an alliance of progressive Anglicans and secular reformers had gained a secure foothold within these institutions and non-Anglicans, and also for the first time women students, entered the colleges. At the same time, a number of liberal Oxbridge dons became the vanguard of the ‘extension movement’ that led to the establishment of new colleges and universities throughout the country. The extension movement was the liberal elite’s response to the 1867 franchise extension, in which anxiety about democracy fostered a resolve to educate citizens so they might cast their vote responsibly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My core discovery was that the reform of Oxbridge and the establishment of new national institutions of higher education was the unstated premise upon which Marshall’s neoclassical economics was built. Classical economics envisages a homogenous labour force paid from past profits. The young Marshall broke the straitjacket of this model by reasoning that an injection of education changed all the relationships: the educated worker was more productive but demanded higher wages, but firms could borrow to cover their higher wage bill. Moving away from a single model, in which two classes of capitalists and workers contest division of a fixed fund, Marshall envisaged a multitude of labour markets in which wages correspond to productivity. Essentially, Marshall was saying that universal higher education would not only train citizens but also usher in a new kind of economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In England, then, neoclassical economics was born from the progressive liberal push that established many of our current institutions of higher education. But between Marshall’s 1873 dream of a competitive, classless society, and Tony Blair’s Marshallian election platform 124 years later, something untoward occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1873 economics was one of several Cambridge moral sciences, of which philosophy was queen. Marshall subscribed to the Idealist conviction that the human personality is not mechanical and therefore accepted that education and research cannot be entirely reduced to system. Consequently, he envisaged the university, the foundation of the new economy, as standing in part outside it. But by 1903 Marshall had established economics as an independent discipline. Freed from humanistic constraints, a newly autonomous neoclassical discourse gradually extended itself into all spheres of public policy debate. Today, Frankenstein’s monster has consumed its parent and the result is called the neoliberal university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the obvious moral of this story is that we have lost today any sure framework of values that can hold the economizing mind at bay. Yet this loss seems built into the modernization of the English universities. Academic specialization is just Adam Smith’s principle of the division of labour applied to institutions of research. But such division is merely fragmentation unless some kind of co-ordination and overall supervision is in place. Hence, university government and administrators. Traditionally, the university has been an independent and self-governing institution, its decision-making body the university senate, composed of the professors of the various disciplines. But self-government requires some consensus on the mission and purpose of the institution as a whole, not simply its various faculties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early Victorian Cambridge the governing supervision was clerical, and theology exercised an invisible yet omniscient check on all academic ventures. In the last decades of the nineteenth century some aspects of this central ideology were taken over by philosophy. But once the various faculties of the humanities and social sciences became autonomous the intellectual center was lost. Vague, undeveloped, and increasingly outdated notions of Max Weber’s vision of science as a vocation held things together for several decades. But when in the 1980s vice-chancellors who knew which way the political wind was blowing began to take control from the university senates, they met no effective internal resistance. Today university self-government has given way to rule by professional administrators, who enforce their own discipline of efficient resource allocation and quality control on a disgruntled academic workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet those who today rail against the neoliberal university usually ignore, and perhaps fail to even see, a related yet more profound problem. For if disciplinary autonomy undermined the ideal of scholarship as a vocation, it has also undermined scholarship itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever you might feel about neoclassical economics, I think there can be no doubt about Marshall’s intellectual creativity. And what is striking here is that his innovations were carried out in an environment in which political economy was not hermetically isolated from other disciplines. Indeed, my research revealed that his achievement rested upon substantial borrowings from philosophy, psychology, and contemporary historical scholarship. Contrast this ‘multi-disciplinary’ reformation of political economy in the face of a changing social reality with the revelation of imperial nakedness that marked the response of professional economists to the 2009 financial crisis. Since Marshall, neoclassical economics has been thoroughly mathematicised and an array of techniques have been added to the professional economist’s toolbox; but any progress in dealing with real world problems on any level beyond the ideological may be seriously doubted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subsequent research has reinforced my suspicions. Back in 2004 I discovered in the archive a long essay that the young Marshall had written on the history of the world. Historians of economics had ignored it because they assumed that an essay on history could have no connection to Marshall’s economic thought. The essay became a vital part of my reconstruction of Marshall’s early economic work; but I also became fascinated with the historical vision it embodied and have since dedicated several years to tracing its origins and subsequent fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investigation has led to the unearthing of an entirely forgotten episode in early twentieth-century English intellectual history. Between around 1910 and 1924, a newly established faculty of Anthropology at Cambridge saw the coming together of field anthropologists (recently returned from the Torres Straits), experimental psychologists, Classical archaeologists and Anglo-Saxonists, who together began to develop a new social theory founded upon the idea that the contact of peoples had been (and remained) the key driving force of human history. This truly ‘inter-disciplinary’ research project floundered with the death in 1922 of one of its key figures, W.H.R. Rivers, and sank into the sand in the wake of Bronisław Malinowski’s success in establishing anthropology as an autonomous discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether or not the theories of the Cambridge ‘anthropologists’ were correct is not the point here. What matters is that their passing marked the end of a remarkable period of university life, in which the foundations of the modern research institute were laid but academic specialization had not yet limited researchers to communicating with a handful of fellow-specialists and a captive-audience of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I take from these two episodes of Cambridge history is that a university can be a site of astonishingly creative cross-disciplinary work, but that once disciplinary boundaries have ossified, it usually is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me jump from the early twentieth century to the present day. As an independent scholar I earn my living as a freelance academic editor. I have a busy period in the autumn when I receive floods of grant applications to edit. A good number of these propose ‘inter-disciplinary’ conferences and longer-term projects on various themes. They always explain how the proposed meeting of minds from different disciplines will enrich our understanding and generate new paradigms, and so on. Then, at other times of the year, I’m occasionally asked to edit a collected volume that has emerged from an earlier such project. And what I am invariably confronted with is a series of chapters by distinguished scholars, each writing from his or her own discipline, with no one essay having any relationship whatsoever with the other essays in the volume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within my own admittedly obscure field of intellectual history, disciplinary specialization does not simply stultify, it generates fundamentally flawed scholarship. Both my work on Marshall and my discovery of the ‘contact of peoples’ anthropologists break new ground. Nobody has noticed these things before. But this is less testimony to my research abilities than indictment of the disciplinary histories that inform conventional understandings of the intellectual past. A disciplinary history is the work of a practitioner of a discipline who projects that discipline back into history and so discovers a past populated by modern university professionals &lt;em&gt;avant la lettre&lt;/em&gt;. The past might be a foreign country, but to the disciplinary historian in an age of globalization all countries look the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On becoming an independent scholar my research and writing improved substantially. After a while I realized that this was because I no longer had ready access to reams of secondary literature via JSTOR and the like and had to focus my attention pretty much exclusively on the primary literature (much of which I could access free through the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/texts&quot;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;). In my own field most of the secondary literature is tripe and reading it harmful to genuine illumination of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize that my research shines a light upon only a very limited world, and that my own experiences as an intellectual historian are narrow in relation to the wider world of research and learning. Nevertheless, it is all too easy to forget that the monopolization of scholarship by the universities is a relatively recent phenomenon. Most of the canonical authors – who were named as such in the early periods of disciplinary formation – worked outside established institutions. And while the likes of Coleridge and J.S. Mill laboured as ‘independent scholars’ &lt;em&gt;avant la lettre&lt;/em&gt;, their Oxbridge contemporaries were charged with instilling correct Anglican doctrines in the ‘rising generation’. A good part of the knowledge produced and taught by today’s academics strikes me as no less safe, vapid, and moribund as that disseminated by their counterparts a century and a half ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thou shalt not worship projects nor&lt;br /&gt;
Shalt thou or thine bow down before &lt;br /&gt;
   Administration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Under Which Lyre’, W.H. Auden. 1946.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bibliogaphy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read most of the research on which I draw on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://yemachine.academia.edu/simoncook&quot;&gt;academia.edu&lt;/a&gt; page. The research on Marshall is set out in my 2009 book, but some of the relevant arguments are summarized in the second part of my essay on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.academia.edu/2305457/Culture_and_Political_Economy_Adam_Smith_and_Alfred_Marshall&quot;&gt;‘Culture and Political Economy’&lt;/a&gt;. For a sustained polemic on modern disciplinary histories see my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.academia.edu/23820170/The_Tragedy_of_Cambridge_Anthropology_Edwardian_Historical_Thought_and_the_Contact_of_Peoples&quot;&gt;‘The Tragedy of Cambridge Anthropology’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For detailed accounts of the emergence of the neoliberal university in Britain from the 1980s on see Keith Tribe’s ‘Educational Economies’ (2006) and his working paper ‘The “Form” of “Reform”: The Postwar University in Britain, 1945-1992’, both available on Keith’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://independent.academia.edu/KeithTribe&quot;&gt;academia.edu page&lt;/a&gt;. (And note, by the way, that Keith is also an independent scholar.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reflections as a whole were inspired by my reading of an early draft of Gregory C. G. Moore’s forthcoming Rounded Globe eBook, &lt;a href=&quot;https://roundedglobe.com/books/d8b165e7-9d86-435c-b339-17cc350dd2e8/Leslie%20Stephen%20and%20the%20Clubbable%20Men%20of%20Radical%20London:%20An%20Essay%20in%20Honour%20of%20John%20King&#39;s%20Retirement/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Leslie Stephen and the Clubbable Men of Radical London: An Essay in Honour of John King’s Retirement&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Header image&lt;/strong&gt;: Daniel Mennerich, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/danielmennerich/8478731666/&quot;&gt;Uxmal MEX - Pyramid of the Magician 04&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Chanctonbury Ring</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/chanctonbury-ring/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/chanctonbury-ring</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://prehistories.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/chanctonbury-hill-01-coloured.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://prehistories.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/chanctonbury-hill-01-coloured.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://prehistories.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/chanctonbury-hill-02-coloured.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://prehistories.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/chanctonbury-hill-02-coloured.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://prehistories.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Prehistories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The folklore associated with Chanctonbury Ring in Sussex is endless. Read more &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussexarch.org.uk/saaf/chanctonbury.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired to make this comic after listening to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bleedingheartrecordings.com/cuz/cuz.htm&quot;&gt;The Wheel and the Ring&lt;/a&gt; by Cuz.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Of mustard and manure</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/mustard-and-manure/"/>
   <updated>2016-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/mustard-and-manure</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fourth in a series of posts by Dr Mark McKerracher on the origins of agriculture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every now and again agricultural archaeology and related disciplines hit the headlines. This latest post was inspired by a couple of pieces of new research, which the BBC flagged a couple of years ago, and which indicate a hitherto unexpected sophisication of farming and diet in prehistory. And, better yet, the original research article (Saul et al. 2013)is open access so you can see it for yourself &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0070583&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The results are from ‘The Baltic Foragers and Early Farmers Ceramic Research Project’, in which Mesolithic and Neolithic pottery from modern Denmark and northern Germany were examined for food residues. Now, I’d heard of lipid residue analysis before, but in this case the evidence comes from phytoliths preserved in charred residues on the pottery. Literally, phytolith translates as something like ‘plant-stone’: they are the remains of an insoluble silica that gets deposited amongst cells in the living plant, and survives even once the plant itself has been burned away. Usefully for us, they can often be identified to family, genus or even species level, allowing us some insight into plant use and ecology (see Cappers &amp;amp; Neef 2012 p.130 for a good brief summary). In this case, the phytoliths point to Alliaria petiolata (M. Bieb) Cavara &amp;amp; Grande – more commonly known as garlic mustard. The context suggests culinary use; the plant gives a strong taste but has negligible nutritional value; hence, those prehistoric chaps and chapesses were apparently spicing their food, simply for the delectable taste. Yum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why not, after all? Why shouldn’t hunter-gatherers and early farmers have been concerned to eat something tastier than hulled wheat, hazelnuts and crab apples? For me, though, this raises the question of gathering vs. cultivation – i.e. were they deliberately growing spices, in a kind of herb garden set-up? This might sound fanciful for the Neolithic but, again, if you can invent agriculture, why not herb gardens?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And talking of Neolithic inventiveness, here’s the second piece of news that interested me: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-23314510&quot;&gt;“Neolithic farmers used manure on crops”&lt;/a&gt;. This one strikes rather closer to home, not just because it came shortly after Dung Awareness Day, but because the work was led by my colleagues, elders and betters at Oxford University. The School of Archaeology even issued its own press release. Neolithic plant remains from across Europe were subjected to stable isotope analysis, and the results indicate that certain crops were manured – a means of fertilisation whose usage wasn’t previously known as early as this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘certain crops’ bit is highly significant, since it implies that the Neolithic farmers were selecting those crops that they thought would benefit the most from manuring, leaving the hardier types to fend for themselves. The lead researcher Dr Amy Bogaard, quoting to the BBC, draws out the wider significance of these findings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These results point to a different kind of farming where they were making fixed investments in land that they intended to hang onto and pass on to future generations…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is cutting-edge stuff, and excitingly we can expect more good things to come, because Dr Bogaard is running an impressive ERC-funded four-year project investigating “The Agricultural Origins of Urban Civilization”, which now has its own &lt;a href=&quot;https://agricurb.com/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; that is well worth keeping an eye on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper has now been published – it’s one of those where the number of authors exceeds the number of pages, demonstrating the wealth of expertise behind these results: Bogaard et al. 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the moral of the story – if any – is that you should never underestimate prehistoric farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MJM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bogaard, A., Fraser, R., Heaton, T.H.E. et al. (2013). ‘Crop manuring and intensive land management by Europe’s first farmers’, Proceedings of the Natural Academy of Sciences 110 (31), pp.12589-12594.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cappers, R.T.J. &amp;amp; Neef, R. (2012). Handbook of Plant Palaeoecology, Groningen/Barkhuis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saul H, Madella M, Fischer A, Glykou A, Hartz S, et al. (2013). &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0070583&quot;&gt;‘Phytoliths in Pottery Reveal the Use of Spice in European Prehistoric Cuisine’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image credit: ‘Garlic Mustard (Alliaria petiolata)’, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/biteyourbum/14836076540/in/photolist-oB1LF7-5KyGJU-ospvuG-cXn2Uw-7XUYgx-hNwaMV-9ssEbM-5KyGXo-rux1Wy-nVuPEF-es3LNU-bQL1jB-6mVWuD-5KyHkQ-5KusLV-G1Cpcd-39nxxQ-ziv3M7-9Dbdh4-6s8wnC-bscu3c-bUfiSA-ex55LZ-bsRhUH-ex8fPh-bsRgTp-7TEFK7-CnftDF-oRtuAu-36WLn-5KyGLd-6spgp1-4PRz9m-nSBw3V-6WekBC-6Wajpe-DJp1YK-7RNDc5-bBE2DE-mV3e9r-soHB1e-83EiJS-4PRxYy-nHR72Z-7UvaC4-2Vvn7D-52MViV-7ZtEG2-7RkDdD-GQ9iPV&quot;&gt;BiteYourBum.com&lt;/a&gt;. Creative Commons license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier posts in this series are: &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/origins-of-british-agriculture/&quot;&gt;Origins of British Agriculture&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/agricultural-strategy/&quot;&gt;Agricultural Strategy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-mists-of-time/&quot;&gt;The Mists of Time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>It&#39;s the Stupidity, Stupid</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/its-the-stupidity-stupid/"/>
   <updated>2016-05-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/its-the-stupidity-stupid</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Intellectual historian Keith Tribe offers a domestic perspective upon the current debate over Britexit from the EU.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been observing recent political events with a sense of deep-seated dismay.  In Britain, the first half of 2015 was dominated domestically by the backwash of the Scottish Independence referendum; internationally, by the circus of the Greek debt crisis, where Tsipras would agree one thing in Brussels and then go home and disown what he had agreed on TV, as if nobody outside Athens watched Greek TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scottish independence vanished from the public agenda of the SNP within a few months of the referendum, with the collapse of the oil price.  Scotland’s prosperity now clearly lies with the current terms of the Union.  Although it should be noted that when in 2013 it looked as though the Grangemouth refinery was to be closed, the real problem was that this one closure would take 10% of the Scottish manufacturing base with it.  In January 2016 Scotland’s non-oil and gas exports to the rest of the United Kingdom were four times that to the rest of the EU and increasing – exports to the rest of the EU had fallen 8% in one year.  So the idea that the path to prosperity lay through an independent Scotland was always a rather flaky idea.  Besides which, actually establishing an independent Scotland could well turn out as costly as the Darien project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much the same is true of the idea that Britain could prosper through leaving the EU.  As Philip Stephens has pointed out in the FT recently, the idea that Britain could “reclaim sovereignty” by leaving the EU is self-refuting: the possibility of leaving is itself confirmation of sovereignty.  Quite apart from the very rudimentary idea of “sovereignty” that those who make such arguments display, detached from any serious consideration of the relationships now existing between European states, or any comprehension of the government of modern polities.  Best estimates of the economic gains from membership of the EU run at about 10%: that Britain is now 10% better off than it would have been had it never been a member of the EU.  Detaching Britain from the EU, and reorganising our political, economic and social relationships with the world’s third-most important political bloc, could well chew through that in short order.  What the dawning new era would be like is anyone’s guess, but there is no particular reason to suppose that it would be any improvement on the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scottish independence could well follow on from Brexit.  The turbulence of Spanish politics could well lead into Catalan independence given the reduced legitimacy of established parties.  In France there is a related lack of support for the mainstream parties of right and left, which only together seem capable of stemming the electoral advance of the Front Nationale.  Similar stories of disaffected voters placing their faith in the politics of anti-politics can be told about Italy, Germany, Greece, The Netherlands, and Denmark.  And on the other side of the Atlantic those with any commitment to serious politics look on aghast as a huckster channelling the ghost of Huey Long steadily treads his path to nomination as the Republican Party presidential nominee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Max Weber noted, modern politics requires the firm, slow boring of hard boards, united with passion and a sense of proportion.  Today many seem to think that passion is enough.  “People” are said to be disaffected from politics and political leadership; a new antipolitics is said to be abroad.  True enough, today some of the leading British parliamentary figures plumb new depths of shallowness.  David Cameron presents himself as the honest broker seeking to save us from a mess he created in the first place by his casual approach to party politics. Tariq Ali tells us in the last &lt;em&gt;London Review of Books&lt;/em&gt; that Jeremy Corbyn articulates a national mood – clearly he does not get out much, nor has he noticed that it is Corbyn’s advisers who seem to do all the articulating, the Labour Party leader being mostly mute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practice of politics in a representative democracy is an unedifying sight.  Representative democracy is however what we have, and the alternatives – plebiscitary democracy, authoritarian democracy, monarchy, dictatorship, oligarchic rule – are all much worse.  We should be grateful for what we have, not be surprised by how imperfect it is.  Our efforts should be directed to improving ourselves and those around us, not blaming remote others for not giving us what we want.  All of the countries and regions mentioned above belong to the wealthiest part of the modern world.  Even being poor in a wealthy country is very rarely much like being even reasonably well-off in a poor country, a point that Adam Smith made long ago.  Articulating this principle in discussion of Europe’s immigration crisis would be helpful.  Simply being alive is a privilege; being alive in a wealthy country confers enormous benefits on those who live there, benefits to which they themselves have directly contributed little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no economic case for Brexit, but that is more or less beside the point.  Extending the line of argument above, being a citizen of an EU member state brings with it social and cultural advantages that, being taken for granted, are usually ignored.  Britain is now more like e.g. Holland than it is like any other non-EU country in the world – not the same, but in many significant ways similar.  Only for tourists and a wealthy elite does the USA look anything like Britain.  The truth of this is confirmed by the progress of Donald Trump through the Republican primaries.  But even here we can find confirmation of Adam Smith’s analysis of commercial society: that its motor is emulation and vanity; translated into the political process, those who already have much of what they need respond to politicians who promise them more of what they already have, which they no longer even notice they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: James Gillray, ‘Monstrous Craws, at a New Coalition Feast (1787)’. Public Domain.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Mists Of Time</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-mists-of-time/"/>
   <updated>2016-05-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-mists-of-time</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The third in a series of posts by Dr Mark McKerracher on the origins of agriculture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing of this post was only ever a matter timing – a question of ‘when’ not ‘if’. Once I’d started an occasional series of blog posts about the origins of agriculture, I knew I’d have to write one (or several) about the very beginnings, the true origins – the first farming in the history of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that time has come, and we shall reach back through the mists of time towards the earliest farmers (and, to be precise, I’m only thinking about arable farming this time)… prompted by an unexpected link, posted on the Association for Environmental Archaeology’s Facebook page, and a recently purchased new book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cappers, R.T.J. &amp;amp; Neef, R. (2012). &lt;em&gt;Handbook of Plant Palaeoecology&lt;/em&gt; (Barkhuis, Groningen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This splendid volume, lavishly illustrated and still surrounded by an aura of new-book-smell, is a thorough guide to plant palaeoecology – or, as some (like me) prefer to call it, archaeobotany. It discusses everything from taxonomy, biology and ecology to preservation, identification and interpretation. Examples are drawn from various sources, in particular the authors’ fieldwork in Egypt, where walnut bark is apparently used for “cleaning teeth and reddening lips”. See the photo on page 12 of such bark for sale at a Cairo market, advertised as “Lady Toots-brush” – surely the perfect name for a pop diva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I digress. I recommend this book and may come back to it in future posts, but its main relevance to this post is that it has a section entitled “Modelling the dawn of farming” (pp.375-80), a handy summary guide to, well, the dawn of farming. It’s a pretty complex area of debate, and not my particular area of expertise, but some basic points are worthy of note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The period in question is the Neolithic, more specifically the self-explanatory “Pre-Pottery Neolithic” period, over 10,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The area in question may broadly be described as Western Asia, with particular importance being commonly attached to the biblical lands of the so-called “Fertile Crescent”, running from the valley of the Jordan, north up the Levantine coast, bending around south-east Turkey and Syria, and following the Euphrates and Tigris down to the Persian Gulf.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/fcmap.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fcmap.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Norman Einstein, based on a similar map from the 1994 edition of the &lt;em&gt;Encyclopedia Britannica&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=471913&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The basic process at work is something like this: hunter-gatherers gathering wild food plants and sowing their seeds, and harvesting the result, and so on; this proto-agricultural process, somewhere between wildlife management and full-blown farming, resulted in the domestication of crops – whereby certain (genetic) characteristics offered a competitive advantage under cultivation, but not in the wild. For example, in the wild it’s advantageous to have good seed dispersal mechanisms, to increase chances of germination in the next generation. But under cultivation, this is disadvantageous: successful reproduction comes not from shattering your seeds all over the place, but from having your seeds harvested and resown as seed-corn. For an excellent, informed discussion of crop domestication see Fuller 2007.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this topic raises a number of pressing questions. Radiocarbon-dated crop remains indicate, on current evidence, that the cultivation and domestication of, e.g. wheat, occurred first of all around the Levant – but it’s less clear whether the same ‘discovery’ occurred at other places independently, or whether everyone else got the idea from the Levant. The latter model is a bit – dare I lapse into the vernacular? – a bit old school. A bit “diffusionist”, as they say on the street. But to support the other model, the ‘multiple independent origins’ model, you’d need to find and date other domesticated crop remains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now to that article that I was led to unexpectedly via Facebook: “Farming Was So Nice, It Was Invented At Least Twice”, on ScienceNOW, reporting on an original research paper in Science itself (Riehl et al. 2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The item reports new research that supports the ‘multiple independent origins’ model: a long, well-dated sequence of plant remains from a site in Iran, suggesting cultivation and domestication not so long after its more westerly Levantine counterpart, and apparently independently invented. Suggestive, but not conclusive – partly because radiocarbon dates aren’t quite precise enough. If you’ve got access to &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;, another paper in the same issue by George Willcox helps to put all this in perspective (Willcox 2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my series of posts on Rounded Globe has finally scratch-ploughed the surface of the very origins of agriculture. There’s clearly a fascinating and epic story waiting to be told here, with ambitious new research constantly building up our picture (did I mention genetic profiling?), and if/when I have time I’d love to explore this all in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MJM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fuller, D.Q. (2007). ‘Contrasting patterns in crop domestication and domestication rates: recent archaeobotanical insights from the Old World’, Annals of Botany 100, pp.903-924.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riehl, S., Zeidi, M., &amp;amp; Conard, N.J. (2013). ‘Emergence of Agriculture in the Foothills of the Zagros Mountains of Iran’, Science 341 (no.6141), pp.65-67.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willcox, G. (2013). ‘The Roots of Cultivation in Southwestern Asia’, Science 341 (no.6141), pp.39-40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image credit: Wolfgang Sauber: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=7260399&quot;&gt;Neolithic Sickle&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier posts in this series are: &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/origins-of-british-agriculture/&quot;&gt;Origins of British Agriculture&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/agricultural-strategy/&quot;&gt;Agricultural Strategy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What is a Professor?</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/what-is-a-professor/"/>
   <updated>2016-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/what-is-a-professor</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Herb Childress turns his gaze from the supply of knowledge to the people behind it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her son was murdered, and she began to study sociology as a way to understand the world her son had travelled in. She now teaches at a small college, a 5/5 load, trying to bring other students to understanding of the duties of friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He grew up in wheat country, not understanding as a child that the grain elevators and railroad tracks, along with bringing a few jobs in, also took enormous resources away for pennies. “I never heard the word taco until I was twenty-five,” he said. “I never had one until I was twenty-seven.” He now teaches others how to read—and to be curious about—the world around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has published nearly 500 articles in chemistry, and his new college lured him away from a prior position with a lab fund of two million dollars and a job for his wife. He makes two dozen international trips a year, and has not booked his own travel in twenty years. He brings undergraduate students into his lab teams, working alongside postdocs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I decided when I was twelve,” she said, “that I either had to go to college or I’d end up like my family.” She recently used vacation days to attend the funeral of her brother, who’d died of an overdose, following on the history of their father’s similar demise years earlier. She did not tell her faculty colleagues why she was away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She graduated from high school at 17, her BS in mechanical engineering at 21, her PhD in mechanical engineering at 25, and was tenured at a top-tier research university at 31. She brings her school millions of dollars a year in research funding, and has been responsible for dozens of new PhDs from her research group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He works in the registrar’s office at another college, and also DJs on the weekends. He collects international rock music, and once burned a CD of Vietnamese psychedelia for a colleague in his office. He teaches Intro to Sociology at a nearby community college, on their late-night shift from 11:30 pm to 2:30 am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How little we know of those people who stand in front of us. If we become one of them, how little we know of our colleagues. As long as we hold our generic label of “professor” — as opaque a term as “barista” or “waitress” or “soldier,” a nameless servant who does their duty — we are permitted to not know the person. Education can be thought of merely as packets of information being shifted back and forth between invisible entities, like automated stock trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Student,” of course, is equally opaque. But because of their youth and naivete, they’re often more willing to tell us their stories. I had a young woman in tears in my office, believing (incorrectly) that she wasn’t capable of doing the work that her college demanded. “I know I’m only here because of field hockey,” she wept. I had a young man in class who was going to college in order to make enough money to buy back the farm that had been in his family for five generations, that his father had been forced to sell. I had varsity athletes who told me of the galvanized steel pails around the weight room that were there within handy reach, for them to vomit into from overexertion and dehydration in their pre-dawn workouts. I had a student tell me about his mother calling from Taiwan every Saturday morning to find out if he was dating a nice Chinese girl yet, to tell him once again how it would be her death and shame if her grandchildren spoke another language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we leave our homes and become something other? Why do we stand on the far shore and try to welcome various of the refugees escaping their homelands? Why do we become so obsessed by fruit-fly digestive chemistry, or a nineteenth-century political economist, or the ways that teenagers use their communities, that we spend much of a career in isolation, pursuing those ghosts? The answers are as diverse as we are, too often hidden away even from ourselves. If we explored, and shared, the motives and dreams and fears that drive us, perhaps we would do better at the human work of teaching and learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image credit: stu_wp: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/stu_p/2258963618/in/photolist-4rBMbA-5BBJNu-5BxsQV-Gmzue-b45LBH-b45Lsg-7fqz8Y-75VNzf-bbeLzZ-9M2QU4-2ekEw2-eaUuUu-CRZe6-b43D94-b9geWk-b9gBWi-8yd9QY-8ryrsd-rcTJG-dBefCG-foNrqy-7v15SZ-6Kf6sm-8fgAP-dmwFN5-4vd18X-b1xrPt-imdi66-3fZrFN-foyazx-6LF9gm-cDg4sS-b9haHv-nGvq97-8ek5CR-5wojQK-m8Q7gd-nqdjX3-yCBKX-m8PceR-nGpN88-m8Q9ky-9LE3Yq-kPiDTw-5tk6C-pfWqR1-qnS45v-foyaSv-qaDp9m-7WFF1z&quot;&gt;They’re Here&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Enchantment of Learning</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-enchantment-of-learning/"/>
   <updated>2016-04-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-enchantment-of-learning</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Patrick Curry offers this short essay on a subject dear to the heart of our Rounded Globe project, a draft of part of a forthcoming longer paper on the same theme.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wonder of learning, the delight of discovering what (it turns out) you wanted to know, the joy of a new world to inhabit, seen through other than your own habitual eyes – these things are so undervalued in our current educational institutions that we need to take a moment to remind ourselves of what we are talking about. Here are three examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Niccolò Machiavelli has been exiled from Florence to his family farm, and in a letter of 10th December 1513 writes to his friend Francesco Vettori:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On the coming of evening, I return to my house and enter my study, and at the door I take off the day’s clothing, covered with mud and dust, and put on garments regal and courtly; and reclothed appropriately, I enter the ancient courts of men of antiquity where, affectionately received, I partake of that food which only is mine and for which I was born, where I am not too timid to speak with them and ask them the reasons for their actions; and they in their courtesy answer me; and for four hours of time I feel no weariness, I forget every trouble, I do not fear poverty, death does not dismay me; I give myself over entirely to them. (Quoted in White: 183-84)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This passage is usually assumed by modern scholars to be a mere humanist trope, a literary flourish. It is both more respectful and more economical, however, to assume that Machiavelli meant exactly what he said, and that what he describes is just what happened. Or are we too jaded to believe it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another example, in 1934, after a time of sleeping rough in his long walk across Europe, the great travel writer Patrick Leigh Fermor found himself a guest of the British Consul in Sofia. He luxuriated in the hot baths, clean linen and fine food, but ‘Best of all,’ he said, ‘the &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannica&lt;/em&gt;; I leapt at it like a panther’ (Fermor: 8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently still, another writer, Eva Hoffman, recalls emerging from her fortnightly trip to the local library in her Warsaw neighbourhood, the interior of which was ‘a space of mystery and magic, on whose threshold I stand a humble acolyte’: ‘I come out, usually into the dim evening streets, enchanted with what awaits me, and as soon as I come home, I pounce on one of the volumes’ (Hoffman: 26). (Note the pantherine resonance with Leigh Fermor; the soul is hungry for living knowledge, and only that can satisfy it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of relationship with learning – enchanted, and passionately so – is the true benchmark for understanding, appreciating and encouraging its wonder. Let me try to tease out some of the dynamics at work. One is the seriousness of play: improvised but not random, intentional but not goal-directed, and relational, involving other beings, of whatever kind, whether physically present or imaginally. When it takes place free from any attempt to direct or manipulate or use it, play is fundamental to the way we learn how to be ourselves as well as how others tick, how to create and innovate and, perhaps most importantly, how to learn at all. The enchantment resulting from play leads you deeper into whatever you’re doing, which in turn generates a deeper enchantment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of the enchantment of learning is the intrinsic value of what is being learned. As John Henry Newman insisted long ago in &lt;em&gt;The Idea of a University&lt;/em&gt;, ‘any kind of knowledge, if it be really such, is its own reward’. It is valuable not for its instrumental or exchange-value, in order to attain some other goal, no matter what, but, he wrote, ‘for what its very presence does for us’ (Newman 1982 [1853]: 77, 78). And the experience of that presence is one of wonder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an essay of the same title, Simon Leys has restated Newman’s thesis, writing that ‘a university is a place where scholars seek truth, pursue and transmit knowledge for knowledge’s sake – irrespective of the consequences, implications and utility of the endeavour.’ However anachronistic or impractical it may appear, it is necessary, now more than ever, to insist on this humanist ideal, even if only so we can realise how far we have fallen. As Leys says, ‘When a university yields to the utilitarian temptation, it betrays its vocation and sells its soul’, without which it cannot fulfil its very &lt;em&gt;raison d’être&lt;/em&gt; (Leyes: 463, 464).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another dynamic is metaphor. Metaphor is the life-blood of learning, and of the humanities in particular, because there can be no empathic, imaginative or narrative understanding without understanding-&lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt;: without the tensive truth of being, at one and the same time, who you are as the reader, listener, viewer or whatever, and simultaneously (in defiance of Aristotle’s logical laws) as the other person, or indeed thing, you are hearing, watching or reading, or about whom you are reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science has different goals: explanation, prediction, mastery (see the work of Mary Midgley, Paul Feyerabend and many others, including my own &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patrickcurry.co.uk/papers/Rio%20paper%20-%20Feb%202015.pdf&quot;&gt;‘Defending the Humanities in a Time of Ecocide’&lt;/a&gt;). Accordingly, it may start in wonder but can only progress, in its own terms, by trying to ‘resolve’ or otherwise eliminate explicit metaphor, ambiguity and paradox. To quote the Nobel Prize-winning scientist Sir Peter Medawar (in a passage I find quite chilling):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As science advances, particular facts are comprehended within, and therefore in a sense annihilated by, general statements of steadily increasing explanatory power and compass… In all science we are being progressively relieved of the &lt;em&gt;burden&lt;/em&gt; of singular instances, the &lt;em&gt;tyranny&lt;/em&gt; of the particular. (Quoted in Feyerabend: 250, 251; my emphases)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is valued in this case is increasingly generic abstraction, whose ultimate model is mathematics. Contrast this worldview with that of Freya Stark, the great travel writer and essayist, who affirms that ‘truth is &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; average. Since there is not one single thing in the world exactly like another, the very essence of truth is that it leaps across averages to the particular…’ (Stark 2013 [1948]: 81; her emphasis). Certainly this kind of truth is essential to enchantment, whose ‘magic’ is always to be found in and as the ‘concrete’. Indeed, I see it as essential to life itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where metaphor comes in. As its theorist Paul Ricoeur (2003) put it, metaphor discovers as it creates, and makes as it finds. And it does so together with an other, whoever that may be. This is not truth as accurate representation, nor as deductive syllogism, but as relationship and its effects. Hence Weber’s definition of truth, respecting its wildness and autonomy: ‘only that which &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; to be true for all those who &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; the truth’ (quoted in Schaff: 118; original emphases). The contrast with the starveling captive of modern power-knowledge could hardly be clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mode is not about knowing and manipulating an item. It is participatory, both affecting the other party or parties and being affected by them, and the actual individuals involved are of paramount importance. It is above all from and in relationship with a particular (‘concrete’) teacher that one learns, and one does so in a way that includes but transcends any methods or propositional content. This relationality extends to communities of teaching and learning – some of whose members (as in the experience of Machiavelli) may not be present in the narrowly physical sense – and their various traditions. And it leaves thinking as only a process that does not already know, although it may sense, its conclusion in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to have this kind of experience in Gregory Bateson’s classes at the University of California (Santa Cruz) in the mid-70s. It comprised learning new things about both the world and myself, and with each one, a significantly new world and self came into being. But not only that; the excitement was both subtler and more sweeping. To borrow Bateson’s own terms, I was learning how to learn. And that only happened in his presence, in a way that cannot be reduced to concepts alone. Yet I was also aware of the presence, not literally but unmistakably nonetheless, of those from whom he had learned, and learned how to think: Blake, Lamark, his father the scientist William Bateson and, not least, the author of &lt;em&gt;The Book of Job&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick Leigh Fermor, &lt;em&gt;The Broken Road: From the Iron Gates to Mount Athos&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Colin Thubron and Artemis Cooper. London: John Murray, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Feyerabend, &lt;em&gt;Conquest of Abundance: A Tale of Abstraction versus the Richness of Being&lt;/em&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eva Hoffman, &lt;em&gt;Lost in Translation&lt;/em&gt;. London: Vintage Books, 1998.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon Leys, ‘The Idea of a University’. In &lt;em&gt;The Hall of Uselessness: Collected Essays&lt;/em&gt;. New York: NYRB, 2013. pp. 461-64.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Henry Newman, &lt;em&gt;The Idea of a University&lt;/em&gt;. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 1982 [1853].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Ricoeur, &lt;em&gt;The Rule of Metaphor&lt;/em&gt;. Translated by Robert Czerny. London: Routledge, 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lawrence A. Schaff, &lt;em&gt;Fleeing the Iron Cage: Culture, Politics, and Modernity in the Thought of Max Weber&lt;/em&gt;. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1989.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freya Stark, &lt;em&gt;Perseus in the Wind: A Life of Travel&lt;/em&gt;. Tauris Parke, 2013 [1948].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael White, &lt;em&gt;Machiavelli: A Man Misunderstood&lt;/em&gt;. London: Abacus, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Header Image credit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Jonathan Moreau, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonathan_moreau/418008212/in/photolist-CWph9-7KcuX5-htKCQU-iaXmwq-og9Gfe-5po767-oxqxgS-atKSRA-pYodea-2GF8BH-8mDKrW-8zpC5F-esVJcK-oB8WUj-rr6Jcg-9atdRu-9RHPho-osYPf-zXqL7-e4iKjV-eDEqQu-nsEixT-7rGhPa-4xZw6a-CWBUK-4o9oWQ-6uNxhc-f2kxUM-e4iKkM-bHXULX-eajtEZ-6sJh4a-dj5ZW5-r4nLvt-7Fiyvw-aMMsFM-dgcrcF-5wHRbb-8SbXz9-bX3cU7-e4iLA8-9hqyYJ-nhQVoT-bvssmw-8ZNd93-iNpH9k-9gPWs9-rSH7gp-e4iLBB-4SG6h3&quot;&gt;Library Parking Garage&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Tombs in Beowulf</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/tombs-in-beowulf/"/>
   <updated>2016-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/tombs-in-beowulf</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Howard M. R. Williams reports on his recent Grosvenor Lunchtime Lecture, organized by the Department of History and Archaeology of Chester University, “Tombs in ‘Beowulf’.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began my talk by discussing the many material dimensions to the poem &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt; – halls, feasting and martial material culture, and burial mounds. I then introduced the challenge and problems of reading history and archaeology from the poem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poem does indeed shed light on an historical ‘reality,’ but only in the broadest of terms. It reveals the widespread deployment of dimensions of mortuary practices of the 5th-10th centuries in Britain and Scandinavia, including furnished graves, ship-burial, cremation practices and burial mounds. The poem’s fascination with imagined pasts is also revealed in the archaeological record, namely the widespread interest in inserting early medieval graves into prehistoric and Roman monuments before and alongside the widespread adoption of Christian burial traditions and mortuary geographies. Also significant is the way in which the poem reveals a perception of landscape that chimes with the emerging Anglo-Saxon kingdoms of the 7th century onwards. Rather than providing a direct window onto a legendary Migration Period, the poem reveals the rich power of material cultures and landscape in constructing social memories and worldviews for Christian secular elites in the later Anglo-Saxon period, in which the pagan past had a powerful role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration smallimg left&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/hw2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hw2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;The 8th-century Anglo-Saxon crypt at Repton. This may well reflect the kind of environment the Beowulf-poet was trying to evoke as the dwelling of the dragon guarding treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning to the funerals within Beowulf, we must guard ourselves from the seductive desire to equate the poem with the furnished ‘princely’ graves of the 7th century exclusively (including Taplow, Sutton Hoo Mounds 1, 2 and 17, and Prittlewell). A more fruitful approach is to examine the widespread evidence of varying uses of boats and ships in mortuary practices across northern Europe that provide the background to Scyld Scefing’s funeral at the beginning of the poem. Archaeology can not only shed light on the material world of tombs that created inspiration for the poet, but help us to understand the significance of tombs in the poem itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recently published an essay in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/the-lives-of-prehistoric-monuments-in-iron-age-roman-and-medieval-europe-9780198724605?cc=il&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&quot;&gt;collected volume&lt;/a&gt; presenting a fresh perspective on the significance of the dragon’s mound in &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt;. I argued that the archaeological certainty of a Neolithic megalithic monument being depicted in the epic poem is something of an allusion created by archaeologists and a desire to fix a categorical material classification to the monument in the poem. I therefore explored the idea that the monument was a ‘counter-tomb’ with its own biography within the poem itself. As such, it might have been regarded, more than a description of a prehistoric tomb, as a literary antithesis to the subterranean and semi-subterranean crypts containing the graves of kings and saints in middle Anglo-Saxon England. In both regards, my point was to try to query an equation between the poem and the archaeological record in terms of any single period, place or practice. The poem does not preserve traces of a pagan past; rather, it draws on the material world to convey a variety of temporalities and materialities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration smallimg right&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/hw3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hw3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;The Asthall barrow, Oxfordshire: a 7th-century cremation with imported items covered by a prominent burial mound. In broad terms, such funerary practices mirror those afforded to the hero of ‘Beowulf’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandwiched between my discussion in the lecture of Scyld Scefing’s boat-funeral and the dragon’s stone barrow, I also explored the tomb of Beowulf himself in the poem. After his death fighting the dragon, Beowulf is cremated on a headland, close to the dragon’s mound. His pyre is decked with the dragon’s treasure and the mound raised over the pyre subsequently serves as a waymarker for mariners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggested that this funeral needs renewed attention. Scholars need to re-engage with the importance of cremation followed by mound-building – as described in the poem – as a widespread practice in Early Medieval Europe. Rather than trying to pin down a single source of inspiration for the poet, we can more profitably apply our transformed archaeological and anthropological understanding of cremation practices themselves worldwide, and in the early Middle Ages in particular, to the poem. In other words, in place of an attempt to find through archaeology the material ‘reality’ behind the poem, a combination of archaeology and a reading of the poem can demonstrate the varying and complex efficacies of cremation performances followed by mound-building in the construction of social memory and for myth making strategies among early medieval communities. Here lies the direction for future research…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images in article are the authors.
Header image credit: Hembo Pagi, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/hembo/5522375386/&quot;&gt;West Kennet Long Barrow&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Call for Submissions</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/call-for-submissions/"/>
   <updated>2016-04-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/call-for-submissions</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rounded Globe: call for submissions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rounded Globe seek monographs and ‘pamphlets’ (manuscripts of between 10,000 and 30,000 words) from distinguished academics, innovative researchers, and independent scholars. Authors must avoid jargon and consent to publish under a legal license that allows their work to be freely shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All submissions that pass an initial editorial examination are sent out to two external readers for evaluation, one inside the particular discipline and one outside to ensure that the content is clear and intelligible to a general reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We publish a maximum of twelve new essays each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholarly writing has become inaccessible. Highly technical, narrowly focused, and massively overpriced, articles and books in the humanities are written for a tiny audience of fellow specialists and a captive audience of students. This is a poor return for a dedicated lifetime of exhaustive research and careful thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rounded Globe look to the many thousands of &lt;strong&gt;curious humans&lt;/strong&gt; both within and without the universities who thirst to engage with genuine erudition and recognize and value the fruit of intensive scholarly labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rounded Globe’s distribution model is based upon &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt;. Scholars publish with us because they want to introduce their work to a wider public. Our readers trust our authors with their time and mental effort. Our &lt;strong&gt;authors&lt;/strong&gt; trust our &lt;strong&gt;readers&lt;/strong&gt; to give something back in return for a gift of time, expertise, and scholarly craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please send a pitch or completed manuscript to roundedglobe@gmail.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.com/faq&quot;&gt;FAQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rounded Globe header image: Dasha Lebesheva.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Southgate on Voices</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/southgate-on-voices/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/southgate-on-voices</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beverley Southgate criticizes the representation of the work of the historian in Bryn Hammond’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.com/book/54f6f692a26359d553f3348e/Voices%20from%20the%20Twelfth-Century%20Steppe&quot;&gt;Voices from the Twelfth-Century Steppe&lt;/a&gt;, recently published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.com&quot;&gt;Rounded Globe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bryn Hammond provides a specific study that explicitly raises questions of wider historiographical interest. Her primary concern is to excite more people about what might seem (to a Eurocentric historian) quite an esoteric subject: epic records from the steppes of the Mongol empire. I am certainly not competent to comment on that subject-matter; but the author indicates throughout how her material impinges on the more general question of history’s relationship with fiction – and that is something I discussed in my &lt;em&gt;History Meets Fiction&lt;/em&gt; (2009), and is a subject that continues to interest me. My main argument here is that Hammond over-estimates the difference between the two genres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an historical novelist, she approves of the approach to history adopted by the authors of her main text, the &lt;em&gt;Secret History of the Mongols&lt;/em&gt;. As with other ‘secret histories’ (such as date back at least to Procopius in the sixth century), this records aspects of the past that some might have preferred forgotten. It incorporates inscriptions and oral traditions that embrace personal memories, and it is variously written in both prose and verse. These characteristics, Hammond insists, mark it out – distinguish it – from conventional histories, and show it as more akin to her own compositions as a novelist. For historians in her view are far more constrained within the limits and limitations of their empirical evidence; they don’t indulge in speculation or ‘conjecture’, since their ultimate concern is to present a coherent narrative of ‘what actually happened’. Such constrained histories, she accuses, amount to little more than ‘an impoverished string of facts’ (50-1); and one might be reminded here of Dickens’ Thomas Gradgrind in &lt;em&gt;Hard Times&lt;/em&gt;, and his obsession with ‘facts’ at the expense of imagination or any sense of ‘wonder’. That image of the ‘dryasdust’ historian seems still to live on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But surely this is a caricature of what historians actually do and aim to do? No less than novelists, their job is not just to collect ‘facts’ – or remnants of the past that constitute evidence – but to make sense of those building-blocks, by incorporating them into a narrative, a story that for them rings ‘true’. That story will not be found in their materials, but must be imposed upon them. For there is no inherent ‘meaning’ in the past, or in what survives from it: it is either historians or novelists – or anyone else – who are needed to give it any meaning. In other words, since ‘the past’ is irretrievably gone, and beyond anyone’s ability to access directly, it makes no sense to talk of any ‘true’ representations of it; there is just no way of testing ‘the truth’ of any claims made, either by historians or by novelists. Both are engaged in imaginatively constructing an edifice that stands for the moment, but may need modification in the light of new materials or changed perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it really makes no sense to claim, as Bryn Hammond does, that novelists are in some sense more free to make of the past what they will – not, that is, if they claim to be ‘&lt;em&gt;historical&lt;/em&gt;’ novelists who base their work on what actually happened in the past. And Hammond certainly seems concerned to retrieve something of that past – claiming indeed that novelists can do that more effectively than historians, inasmuch as they can take their time to understand texts in their own terms. Having no axe to grind, novelists can take an interest, not only in what actually happened, but in what might have happened and what nearly happened (108). They can, she writes, follow ‘the sense behind the scenes’ (21), examining leads that might not have been taken up in real life; they can read between the lines, and make psychologically based inferences that would lie beyond the scope of conventional histories. (These include the exploration of such abstractions as Mongols’ self-imaginings and self-understanding (50-1), the accommodation of ‘irrational behaviour’, ‘thoughts and feelings’, and ‘people’s inner lives’ (69-70).) And importantly novelists become able in this way to open up sight of possible alternatives – which makes them better able to avoid the appearance of ‘inevitability’, and ‘restore indeterminacy, contingency, accident’ (31).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I have to say that, as Bryn Hammond describes what she endeavours to do as a novelist, it all sounds rather familiar – as being just what contemporary historians are doing. Indeed, I have recently been reading Lytton Strachey’s (early twentieth-century) account of the psychological complexities and personal inconsistencies in the characters of Victorians whose lives he was writing; historians, he writes, should aim at such ‘&lt;em&gt;imaginative comprehension&lt;/em&gt;’ of people in the past as would enable us to ‘move with ease among their familiar essential &lt;em&gt;feelings&lt;/em&gt;’. So attempts by historians to understand ‘inner lives’ is nothing new. (And surely, even Thucydides in the fifth century BC had to try to understand his subjects’ psychology in order to assess their motivations and put authentic-sounding words into their mouths?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, then, Bryn Hammond seems unaware of more recent historiographical developments, in terms of which ‘history’ is perceived, no longer as a ‘science’, but as an ‘artform’. That implies recognition that historians are required to use their &lt;em&gt;imaginations&lt;/em&gt; to create their various stories about the past. Those stories, like those of novelists, will be based on evidence from the past, but must inevitably go beyond the empirical; they will be subjective attempts to impose meaning from a particular standpoint – so they will be admittedly contingent and provisional, with due recognition of the possibility of alternatives; and they will be replaceable (and no doubt replaced) in due course. And they will, further – in defiance of Hammond’s characterisation – take due account of &lt;em&gt;discontinuities&lt;/em&gt;: there has been much criticism lately of those smooth, supposedly all-embracing narratives that contrive to ‘normalise’ and comfort readers rather than unsettle them. (See e.g. Primo Levi, Claude Lanzmann, and Saul Friedländer on the Holocaust, and more generally Hayden White and other theorists.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As introduced by Bryn Hammond, then, the &lt;em&gt;Secret History of the Mongols&lt;/em&gt; can be taken as an example of what ‘history’ should be: written in both prose and poetry, it portrays not only external acts, but also internal ‘mental and emotional states’; it is concerned with conveying psychological insights as much as describing physical events with empirically based evidence. It is small wonder that three of its earlier commentators, approved by Hammond herself, are &lt;em&gt;historians&lt;/em&gt; whose methodology, as she admits, exactly parallels her own (109).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude: both author and publisher are to be congratulated on bringing this subject, with its attendant historiographical issues, to a much wider readership in an easily accessible form; and I hope that what they have provided will form a convenient platform for further discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/bernd_thaller/23955458716/in/photolist-CuRZhh-4kPqp7-n2ta5-xjaXMB-dUcGTv-3pMrLw-ekS28c-nRV7ym-b7VSd2-c3Gocy-xDy9YZ-xsKj73-7kvAaq-b9zfHT-zRqw4n-5g6Ne7-Cdy4gB-nRUy66-z2Q6f7-Cdxfsg-cS4JWS-dnVnka-CDc5oT-dpotUb-c461Y-yqFce6-n2t7N-yPnj8S-9S6Uou-wRXijB-6xXrhe-wEsQKy-nRTbYh-BoeZJQ-obpeqf-awfD18-n2t5F-3pLRpQ-Bhde8n-n2t41-2wgogt-n4P7Y-osBZHp-z4DEzQ-n4BEd-5g93C5-zbsziW-nRTBEw-yruAGM-o9eo1s&quot;&gt;Bernd Thaller&lt;/a&gt;, ‘Rainbow in Mongolia’. Creative Commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Spirit of Mordor</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-spirit-of-Mordor/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/the-spirit-of-Mordor</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To celebrate Tolkien reading day, Tom Hillman discusses the Old English word&lt;/em&gt; Morþorhete &lt;em&gt;and the Spirit of Mordor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day after Sam rescues Frodo from the tower of Cirith Ungol, two orcs, an Uruk and a smaller tracker, nearly catch them, but a fight breaks out between them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The big orc, spear in hand, leapt after him. But the tracker, springing behind a stone, put an arrow in his eye as he ran up, and he fell with a crash. The other ran off across the valley and disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For a while the hobbits sat in silence. At length Sam stirred. ‘Well I call that neat as neat,’ he said. ‘If this nice friendliness would spread about in Mordor, half our trouble would be over.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘Quietly, Sam,’ Frodo whispered. ‘There may be others about. We have evidently had a very narrow escape, and the hunt was hotter on our tracks than we guessed. But that is the spirit of Mordor, Sam; and it has spread to every corner of it. Orcs have always behaved like that, or so all tales say, when they are on their own. But you can’t get much hope out of it. They hate us far more, altogether and all the time. If those two had seen us, they would have dropped all their quarrel until we were dead.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Return of the King&lt;/em&gt;, ‘The Land of Shadow’)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is often the case with Tolkien a glance at &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt; can prove interesting. For in line 1105 we encounter a word that suits the orcs and Frodo’s description of them perfectly.  It is &lt;em&gt;morþorhete&lt;/em&gt;, a compound of &lt;em&gt;morþor&lt;/em&gt;, whose primary meaning is ‘murder’ and from which of course derives ‘Mordor’, and &lt;em&gt;hete&lt;/em&gt;, ‘hate.’ &lt;em&gt;Morþorhete&lt;/em&gt;, occurring only here in extant Old English, denotes a murderous or deadly hatred. Keep in mind, moreover, that every time we see orcs interacting with each other, whether they are of different kinds, as here, of different loyalties (&lt;em&gt;Two Towers&lt;/em&gt;, ‘The Uruk-hai’), or of different commands (&lt;em&gt;Two Towers&lt;/em&gt;, ‘The Choices of Master Samwise’; &lt;em&gt;Return of the King&lt;/em&gt;, ‘The Tower of Cirith Ungol’), they always come to blows. So the word is generally applicable to orcs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt; the word appears in the account of the oath that was meant to restore peace after the attack on Finnsburgh:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ða hie getruwedon    on twa healfa                        1095
fæste frioðuwære.    Fin Hengeste       &lt;br /&gt;
elne unflitme    aðum benemde
þæt he þa wealafe    weotena dome
arum heolde,    þæt ðær ænig mon
wordum ne worcum    wære ne bræce,                   1100
(ne) þurh inwitsearo    æfre gemænden,
ðeah hie hira beaggyfan    banan folgedon,
ðeodenlease,    þa him swa geþearfod wæs.
Gyf þonne Frysna hwylc    frecnen spræce
ðæs morþorhetes    myndgiend wære,                    1105
þonne hit sweordes ecg    syððan scede.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then they concluded strong terms
Of peace for both sides. Finn declared
On oath to Hengest, nobly, with no dispute,
That he, by the authority of his council,
And with acts of kindness, would rule
The sad remnant, that neither by word
Nor by deed would any man break the accord,
Nor through malice would they ever complain –
Though, kingless now, they followed the killer
Of their generous lord: it had been
Necessary for them. Then if any of the Frisians
With reckless speech called to mind
Their murderous hate, a sword would settle it.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The connection here is not to be found in the details of the story of Finn and Hengest, but in the &lt;em&gt;morþorhete&lt;/em&gt; that remains alive just below the surface, so ready to break forth that only the threat of violence can suppress it even temporarily.  In the end the terms do not prove strong enough, any more for Finn and Hengest than for the orcs Frodo and Sam see in Mordor.  A passion so strong can unite or divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; The translation offered above is mine, based on the text and notes in Klaeber’s &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt; (Toronto, 2014). It may not be elegant, but I believe that it is at least not inaccurate. There are, however, points in the Old English that are not entirely clear, but these do not touch the issue of &lt;em&gt;morþorhete&lt;/em&gt; directly.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Amgalant</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/Amgalant/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/Amgalant</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This week Rounded Globe released Bryn Hammond’s essay on her discipline of historical fiction. Today fellow author John Caviglia discusses Hammond’s historical fiction itself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amgalant One: The Old Ideal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amgalant Two: Tribal Wars&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Bryn Hammond&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two extraordinary works launch a novelized exegesis of &lt;em&gt;The Sacred History of the Mongols&lt;/em&gt;—which recounts the life of Genghis Khan, penned sometime after his death in 1227.  Hammond’s initial volumes expand this slender inspiration (fewer than 200 pages in one English edition) to genuinely epic proportions, creating a rich, compulsively readable, immersive work.  And as the two novels—totaling about 1300 pages—begin a trilogy, a reader might ask why, and how, Hammond has so amplified the original…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to the why, it is clear that—Medievalist to the marrow—she is herself enraptured by the Mongols of the time, above all by the fascinating characters in this history of conquest without parallel, rendered “secret” by time and culture, language and abbreviation.  Implicit, in the cryptic text she studies, are secrets of the soul embedded in the acts and words, the entwined intricacies of these Mongols’ lives, a tribal psychology she unfolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hammond has exhaustively studied every aspect of her enterprise, and it is upon that ocean of research that her prose effortlessly floats, ensuring that the reader will travel in space and time to the cultural moment.  And in that richly elaborated context the Temujin of her text—one day to be known as Genghis Khan—is fashioned into what was prophesied when he was born with a blood clot in his fist. You learn what the Mongols eat (a lot of sheep) and drink (black milk!).  You encounter much more about day-to-day tribal life.  But, essentially, the novel takes you into the minds of the protagonists…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reader comes to see Mongols as Mongols saw each other … and the larger world (I got a new take on ancient China, and that wall intended to keep “barbarians” out).  And that kind of vision is where much of the action takes place in this essentially psychological work.  Interior conflicts….  Interior/exterior conflicts…. Interior monologues….  Interior dialogues….  Plain old dialogues….    And then there are the tribal conferences.  Alliance with the Tartars?  War?  Questions are at the heart of this version of the Mongol enterprise, when the future of much of the world hinged on a shaman’s reading the cracks in a sheep’s scapula.  The rise of Genghis Khan was prophesied indeed, but Hammond portrays it as a chancy, supremely complicated and unfolding thing, lived out in the minds of those who—on horseback and in tents—crafted the largest empire known to man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the fate of Tchingis Khan continues its extraordinary course in &lt;em&gt;Tribal Wars&lt;/em&gt;, the tale expected of a conqueror—his unification of the Mongols (thus the enormous sweep of the steppes) by dint of martial talent, native wit and bloodshed—is well and intricately told.  But less expectedly the story of Temujin, conqueror as human being, is brought to the fore.  In particular his tortured relationship to his blood brother, lover and erstwhile enemy, Jamuqa, is here deepened, developed, and brought to an ending dramatic, and deeply tragic, as any that I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not unfair, I think, to state that Hammond’s writing is intimately epic—immense in the necessity of its scope, intimate in the attention devoted to relationships: Tchingis/Temujin and Jamuqa, Tchingis and Borte (first wife and queen), he and his various generals and subordinates, he and his many allies and antagonists….  This, as opposed to the lovingly lingering descriptions of combat stemming from classic epics such as &lt;em&gt;The Iliad&lt;/em&gt;, which culminate in modern historical novels depicting medieval war, such as Bernard Cornwell’s.  In &lt;em&gt;Tribal Brawls&lt;/em&gt; a battle supremely important to Tchingis is depicted in two pages….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hammond’s portrayal of conquest echoes the intimacy of Elizabethan theater—principal characters on stage, the larger war in the wings revealed by alarums and the tidings of messengers.  Not having read &lt;em&gt;The Secret History of the Mongols&lt;/em&gt;, I do not know how much of such ‘staging’ she imports.  However, she has her own Tchingis say, “Wars are fought in the head, always.”  And it seems to me right to have the reader’s attention led to what is personal in this epic, for in the second volume civil war is eponymously depicted, the steppe fighting itself, so to speak (iconically condensed into the lover/enemy relationship of Tchingis and Jamuqa).  Such steppe people as Tchingis did not woo, he had to conquer to embrace.  Hammond’s Tchingis states: “The whole point of me is freedom for my people.”  Tough love, indeed….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for Hammond’s prose, it is wonderfully her own, rich with word play, sometimes lyrical, at times formal and hieratic, often chortle-out-loud funny, and always dense with resonance.  But there’s an aspect to her voice that at first surprised me.  Hammond is—could it be gleefully?—anachronistic, both in authorial comments and through her Medieval Mongols, who speak contemporary, sometimes slangy language (British at that … so that I had to look up “ta”).  If you are bothered by such anachronism, you will be bothered.  As for me—after brief adjustment—I thoroughly enjoyed the read, for Hammond’s writing, nuanced, never usual, is a good in itself.  And to me at least, her authorial anachronism suggests a Shakespeare play staged in a radically different time and place, so to convey—bass beat under melodies—that the drama is universally human at its core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of surprises, one more thing—I love the strength, depth and wisdom of the women in Amgalant, given a society and a time in which they were a spoil of war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum—as begun—this trilogy is unique and wonderful (though not necessarily easy). Hats off to Hammond for her long, loving and genial discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hammond’s acclaimed &lt;strong&gt;Amgalant&lt;/strong&gt; series can be purchased (in print or electronic form) from her &lt;a href=&quot;http://amgalant.com/amgalant-and-me/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. Her recent essay on the craft of historical fiction can be downloaded for free from &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.com/books&quot;&gt;Rounded Globe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dongdan_Kingdom&quot;&gt;The King of Dongdan Goes Forth&lt;/a&gt;’. Public Domain.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Unix, GNU and Linux</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/unix/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/unix</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Unix is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operating_system&quot;&gt;operating system&lt;/a&gt; (OS) invented in 1969 at Bell Labs by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ken_Thompson&quot;&gt;Ken Thompson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dennis_Ritchie&quot;&gt;Dennis Ritchie&lt;/a&gt; and others. And — due to the flexibility afforded by its modular, collaborative approach to computing — over 40 years later, Unix and its descendants &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usage_share_of_operating_systems#Market_share_by_category&quot;&gt;power the overwhelming majority of the world’s computing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The family of operating systems which descend from Unix are referred to collectively as “*nix”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sites like Google, Facebook, Twitter and the vast majority of websites were built on and run on *nix. Apple’s iPhones, iPads and iPods, Android smartphones and tablets, smart TVs, refrigerators, cameras, cars, watches, set-top boxes — they all run *nix. Unix and its offspring power everything from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raspberry_Pi&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/a&gt; to (all of) the world’s most powerful supercomputers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital age was built on Unix and its descendants. So how did this happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early days of computing, software was shared freely amongst its users and authors, who were often the same people. If you wrote a software tool to perform a particular task you would share it with anyone who wanted it. If I improved that tool then I would share my changes with you and with everyone else. This benefited everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This culture of sharing and co-operating influenced the shape of early software, encouraging the production of small, simple programs intended to be used together to perform complex tasks — rather than complex, monolithic programs that tried to do everything. Smaller, simpler programs were easier to maintain, share, re-use and modify, and could be plugged together to perform complex tasks. Improvements to one small component benefited &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the complex applications of which that small program was a part — helping oneself helped others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bell Labs is a research and development facility which, during the time of Unix’s development, was owned by AT&amp;amp;T and was famous for encouraging undirected, open-ended research. Important inventions and developments that came out of Bell Labs include the transistor, cellular telephony, solar cells, practical lasers, communication satellites, the touch-tone telephone and, of course, Unix. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Kernighan&quot;&gt;Brian Kernighan&lt;/a&gt;, one of the developers of Unix, talks about his time at Bell Labs in the video below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ytvid&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&quot;video&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QFK6RG47bww&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unix, born out of this culture of sharing and co-operation where a collaborative approach was &lt;em&gt;assumed&lt;/em&gt;, embodied what is now referred to as ‘The Unix Philosophy’. The most well-known statement of this philosophy, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_McIlroy&quot;&gt;Doug McIlroy&lt;/a&gt;, goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Write programs that do one thing and do it well. Write programs to work together. Write programs to handle text streams, because that is a universal interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McIlroy adds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The notion of “intricate and beautiful complexities” is almost an oxymoron. Unix programmers vie with each other for “simple and beautiful” honours — a point that’s implicit in these rules, but is well worth making overt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This insistence on simple elegance, modularity, co-operation and text-as-the-universal-interface is a large part of what set Unix apart and is, along with various technical attributes, what has been passed on to Unix’s descendants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unix gained widespread use through the 70s and 80s, particularly in academic and commercial settings but was not really suitable for individual use for a couple of reasons. Firstly, Unix was designed primarily for mainframes and there was little interest amongst its academic and commercial users in transferring it to home computers. Secondly, as a regulated monopoly AT&amp;amp;T were not allowed to sell software, so licensing was difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the personal computer saw broad adoption, the rise of proprietary, commercial software, such as Microsoft’s DOS, eroded the culture of early computing — sharing proprietary software is illegal and modifying it is impossible since the source code is not available. As programs could no longer share and build upon each others’ functionality, software became large, complex and monolithic by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1983, &lt;a href=&quot;https://rms.sexy/&quot;&gt;Richard Stallman&lt;/a&gt;, an artificial intelligence researcher at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, began the GNU project, the aim of which was to create an entirely free version of the Unix operating system (GNU stands for “GNU’s not Unix”). “Free”, in this context, means “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html&quot;&gt;free as in freedom, not free as in beer&lt;/a&gt;”, a notion circumscribed by what Stallman called ‘the Four Freedoms’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The freedom to run the program as you wish, for any purpose (freedom 0).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The freedom to study how the program works, and change it so it does your computing as you wish (freedom 1). Access to the source code is a precondition for this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The freedom to redistribute copies so you can help your neighbor (freedom 2).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The freedom to distribute copies of your modified versions to others (freedom 3). By doing this you can give the whole community a chance to benefit from your changes. Access to the source code is a precondition for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to ensure that these freedoms remained intact as software was modified and shared, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-3.0.en.html&quot;&gt;GNU General Public License&lt;/a&gt; (GPL) was created. Similar to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/a&gt; license used on &lt;em&gt;Rounded Globe&lt;/em&gt;, the GPL employs a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyleft&quot;&gt;copyleft&lt;/a&gt; mechanism that ensures that no one can close the software down and/or make a proprietary version — the software will be free for everyone, forever, for any purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1991, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linus_Torvalds&quot;&gt;Linus Torvalds&lt;/a&gt;, a computer science student at the University of Helsinki, created the Linux kernel because he wanted Unix on his personal home computer. The kernel is the ‘bottom layer’ of the operating system; it is the intermediary between other software and the hardware — the final core component that the GNU project lacked. The resulting operating system — a complete, free Unix — is called GNU/Linux, though it is most often just referred to as Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linux exists today as a free universal operating system that embodies the continuation of the culture of early computing — it is produced, maintained and distributed by thousands of people all around the world. It powers the internet and has allowed companies like Google, Twitter and Facebook to create businesses without being crippled by software licensing costs (there are none). It runs smartphones, laptops, tablets, Kindles and watches. It’s allowed the Raspberry Pi to bring accessible, malleable computing to classrooms and individuals without licensing costs. It runs the computers at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CERN&quot;&gt;CERN&lt;/a&gt;, it’s on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curiosity_%28rover%29&quot;&gt;Curiosity Mars rover&lt;/a&gt;, it’s aboard the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Space_Station&quot;&gt;International Space Station&lt;/a&gt; and it runs &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.techrepublic.com/article/how-munich-rejected-steve-ballmer-and-kicked-microsoft-out-of-the-city/&quot;&gt;Munich&lt;/a&gt;. Unless you live in a cave, you use Linux many times every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps Linux’s most surprising achievement, though, is getting huge, commercial entities like Google, Samsung, IBM, Toyota and countless others to work collaboratively. They all contribute — through paying developers, sponsorship and other mechanisms — to the Linux kernel and other parts of the operating system. And when they improve Linux for themselves they improve it for everyone else — even their direct competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one arena of computing where *nix &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; dominate is desktop operating systems (i.e. desktop PCs and laptops), where Microsoft’s Windows holds sway. So, while Unix and its progeny have very much defined and shaped the technology of the world in which we live, and virtually &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; computer user interacts with it in some way on a daily basis, most everyday computer users are largely unaware of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to try Linux out on &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; desktop or laptop computer then &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ubuntu.com/desktop&quot;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opensuse.org/&quot;&gt;OpenSUSE&lt;/a&gt; are good places to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ytvid&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&quot;video&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SYRlTISvjww&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Agricultural Strategy</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/agricultural-strategy/"/>
   <updated>2016-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/agricultural-strategy</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The second of a series of posts by Dr Mark McKerracher on the origins of agriculture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question: when is an agricultural strategy not an agricultural strategy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: when it’s a socio-cultural strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cast your mind back to my earlier post about &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/origins-of-british-agriculture/&quot;&gt;Neolithic farming in Britain&lt;/a&gt;.  As you may recall, archaeobotanists Stevens &amp;amp; Fuller (2012) have argued that crop husbandry had something of an abortive start in Britain: fading out around the Middle Neolithic and only returning with a “major upsurge in agricultural activity” in the Middle Bronze Age, from around 1500 BC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said at the time, I’m not a prehistorian, so I’m in no position to critique the model. But I was interested to discover, after writing the earlier post, an article from 2000 which puts a different perspective on things (Brück 2000).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this work came twelve years before Stevens &amp;amp; Fuller’s botanical study, it’s obviously not a rebuttal – nor vice versa, since S&amp;amp;F don’t cite Brück. What it does, however, is suggest a model to explain why things seem to have changed in the Middle Bronze Age. It also provides a corrective to the overtly economic interpretations that have often been placed on the process. Since this period sees the appearance of clearly-defined “farmstead” settlements for the first time, some scholars have suggested that agricultural activity must have intensified in this period – hence also the rise in crops identified by S&amp;amp;F. This all sounds pretty reasonable – unless you think, like Brück, that those Bronze Age folk weren’t actually interested in maximizing productivity. Rather, she suggests that their main reason for creating (relatively) stable farmsteads within spatially defined farming units was a new pattern of social thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll offer a crude oversimplification of Brück’s argument, for laymen like myself, with apologies to specialists for the inaccuracies and misunderstandings. Here goes. In the Neolithic and Early Bronze Age, we’ve got societies without fixed settlements, but with larger-scale, periodic gatherings of extended kin-groups at monumental sites – henges and the like. But from the Middle Bronze Age, you have these relatively stable settlements, as family groups preferred to stress their autonomy – real or ideal – rather than their fluid connections within the wider kin group. In short, as communities came to be defined by a new social order, the farmsteads represent the imposition of a new physical, spatial order. So the new approaches to farming were the &lt;em&gt;result&lt;/em&gt; – rather than the cause – of social change. Of course, we then have to wonder: what caused the social change in the first place? And there’s no easy answer to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t do justice to the hypothesis here. It draws upon waggon-loads of archaeological and anthropological theory (“ontological security”…? ) but it’s compelling, nonetheless. I never realized, before reading this, that I’d often made an implicit assumption that maximising agricultural production is a desirable thing to do. And to an extent, I still think that’s a reasonable assumption. You surely don’t have to be an arch-capitalist to think that a bit more surplus grain might come in useful. But clearly social circumstances will count for a lot. It’s a matter of perspective, and since we’ll never know what the Bronze Age perspective really was, the speculation will no doubt continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MJM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brück, J. (2000). “Settlement, landscape and social identity: the early-middle Bronze Age transition in Wessex, Sussex and the Thames valley” Oxford Journal of Archaeology 19: pp.273-300. My thanks to Dr A. Bogaard for recommending this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image credit: ‘Butser Ancient Farm’, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/gordontour/&quot;&gt;gordontour&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first post in this series is &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.github.io/origins-of-british-agriculture/&quot;&gt;Origins of British Agriculture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Climate Change</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/climate-change/"/>
   <updated>2016-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/climate-change</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;James Palmer, early medievalist at St Andrews, reviews recent discussion of the impact of climate change in late antiquity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late Antique climate change was in the news last week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence being put together by Ulf Büntgen and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pages-igbp.org/ini/wg/euro-med2k/erl-faqs-january-2016&quot;&gt;Euro-Med2k Working Group&lt;/a&gt; about Europe’s changing climate is creating a fantastic resource for understanding better the relationship between climate and the course of history. Some of their conclusions are terrifying, particularly that present average summer temperatures have no parallels over the past 2000 years. Let’s not deny climate change is a real thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet. There is, as my friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ed.ac.uk/history-classics-archaeology/about-us/staff-profiles/profile_tab1_academic.php?uun=mazzolin&quot;&gt;Monica Azzolini&lt;/a&gt; put it last week, a need for a ‘more nuanced environmental history that actually uses both micro-historical tools and macro-historical tools together’. The reporting of what is now being called ‘The Late Antique Little Ice Age’ makes this a real case in point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that there was some environmental change in the period is not new. There have been discussions for years about evidence for a major volcanic eruption around AD536 – an eruption Büntgen now reckons was actually three in relatively quick succession and which forced a drop of maybe up to 4°C in some areas. &lt;a href=&quot;http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k40117&amp;amp;pageid=icb.page188194&quot;&gt;Michael McCormick&lt;/a&gt; has already published articles arguing that environmental instability helped to destabilise the Roman Empire and to provide conditions for the Justinian Pandemic (i.e. plague) of the sixth century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, onto the new reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up, I saw &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.archaeology.wiki/blog/2016/02/09/new-little-ice-age-coincides-fall-eastern-roman-empire-growth-arab-empire/&quot;&gt;‘New “Little Ice Age” coincides with fall of Eastern Roman Empire and growth of Arab Empire’&lt;/a&gt;. In this article, Büntgen is quoted as saying ‘with so many variables, we must remain cautious about environmental cause and political effect, but it is striking how closely this climate change aligns with major upheavals across several regions’. (I like ‘We must remain cautious… but…’ there – a classic academic sidestep). The big story should now apparently be: sixth-century tribes moved from the steppes of northern China, formed an alliance with the East Romans, and helped to defeat the Sasanian Empire in Persia in the early seventh century, paving the way for the rise of the Arab Empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has been ‘explained’ here? As put in the article, the movement of the steppe peoples, prompted by climate change, explains everything that happens thereafter. But it doesn’t. The course of the reign of Herakleios (r.610-641), which covers the defeat of the Persians and the first major successes of the Arabs, was highly complex on almost every conceivable level. Here is the briefest &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.roman-emperors.org/heraclis.htm&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt;. Climate change may explain some aspects of some factors in play, but it does not explain ‘what happened’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there was this story in &lt;em&gt;New Scientist&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newscientist.com/article/2076713-125-year-mini-ice-age-linked-to-the-plague-and-fall-of-empires/?platform=hootsuite&quot;&gt;‘125-year mini ice age linked to plague and fall of empires’&lt;/a&gt;. Again these links are a bit vague. ‘There was dramatic social, cultural, and political change in this period. Perhaps aspects of the changes were exacerbated by a colder period’, suggests Late Romanist/Byzantinist Shaun Tougher. Francis Ludlow adds, ‘ultimately there can be very little doubt that these sorts of abrupt climate events place great stress on societies, and can sometimes tip them over the edge’. Both of these statements are entirely reasonable. Neither of them actually addresses whether the changes in the environment had any actual role to play in the shaping of the events the article is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article finishes with some comments about ‘weather winners’, as some people may have benefited from climate change. Good. Büntgen returns here, suggesting that the Arab conquests of the seventh century may have been helped by increased vegetation caused by climate change. Fine. And Büntgen does not seem to be suggesting that this was ‘the cause of the Arab conquests’. But without any context, it is awkward. There is no suggestion that the Arabs were taking advantage of an East Rome weakened by its recent struggles against the Persian Empire, no suggestion that the leaders were energised by the teaching of Muhammad (d. 632) – there were a lot of political and cultural factors in play, and explaining the Arab conquests on the basis of feeding camels alone is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; why invoking environmental factors remains controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not need to be a competition, environment vs people. Let’s be honest: ‘it was a combination of factors’. Changing climate can trigger important changes. People, being people, respond to these changes in different ways. Tying climactic patterns to large-scale ‘rise and fall’ patterns isn’t necessarily helpful, if it promotes a clunky monocausalism. Sometimes people do things, achieve things, despite what the weather is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was why I was already undertaking my mini &lt;a href=&quot;https://merovingianworld.wordpress.com/2015/10/16/climates-of-crisis/&quot;&gt;‘Climates of Crisis’&lt;/a&gt; project. We need to understand better the ways in which environmental crisis becomes a human crisis. We need to understand how climate changes intersects with political, religious, and cultural thinking. The work of Büntgen and his colleagues is fantastic – and more historians need to bring their tricks to the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image credit: ‘Home less’, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/yasinhasan/&quot;&gt;Yasin Hassan&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Changing Faces of Britain&#39;s Natives</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/changing-faces-of-britain's-natives/"/>
   <updated>2016-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/changing-faces-of-britain's-natives</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Simon J. Cook, Rounded Globe author, shares some of his research into the history of British conceptions of prehistory and the genesis of Tolkien’s hobbits.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late-Victorian histories of the English began in the woods of Schleswig, before the migration to the British Isles. But around 1900 historians decided that English history proper should begin with the foundation of the modern state in the fourteenth century. What came before was deemed not only barbarous but insufficiently documented. The story of ancient Britain, and of the peoples who settled it, was left to a motley crew of archaeologists, folklorists, philologists and, increasingly, writers of fiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Cook1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cook1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Picture from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/ourislandstoryhi00marsuoft&quot;&gt;Our Island Story. A History of England for Boys and Girls&lt;/a&gt;, by H.E. Marshall, illustration by A.S. Forrester (London, 1905).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first section of my Rounded Globe essay on &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.com/book/54f6fe79648a590459746be1/J.R.R.%20Tolkien&#39;s%20Lost%20English%20Mythology&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;J.R.R. Tolkien’s Lost English Mythology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’ve discussed some facets of the early twentieth-century search for the ancient English; in this post I track the changing face of Britain’s natives. The picture above depicts a sort of ancient ‘close encounters’ moment: native Britons watch the arrival of the Roman fleet of Julius Caesar. This captures the conventional Victorian image of the Romans bringing civilization to a savage island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare the primitive Britons above, barefoot and attired in rude animal skins, with the blond giants below. Although this second picture was published earlier, it embodies a newer kind of historical thinking. These iron-age warriors are still Britons, but they are no longer natives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Cook2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cook2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Picture from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/bericthebriton00hentrich&quot;&gt;Beric the Briton. A Story of the Roman Invasion&lt;/a&gt;, by G.A. Henty, illustrator unknown (London, 1893).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For much of the nineteenth century it was assumed that Britain had been settled for only a few generations before the coming of the Romans. But this view became untenable after 1877 and the publication of Canon William Greenwell’s &lt;em&gt;British Barrows&lt;/em&gt;. From his meticulous and extensive archaeological excavations, Greenwell drew the conclusion that prehistoric long barrows were not only older than round barrows, but had been built by a different people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Cook3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cook3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Image from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/britishbarrowsre00gree&quot;&gt;British Barrows. A record of the examination of the sepulchral mounds in various parts of England&lt;/a&gt;, by W. Greenwell (Oxford, 1877).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Greenwell it was generally accepted that the Celtic-speaking Britons, the supposed makers of the round barrows, had intruded upon an earlier population. The result was the rehabilitation of the Britons: no longer the passive victims of history, conquered and pushed aside by more vigorous peoples, the Britons became invading immigrants in their own right – ancient barbarians, maybe, yet virtuous and worthy ancestors for the modern British. In the caption of the second picture above the leading Briton declares: ‘Tell Suetonius that we scorn his mercy and will die as we have lived, free men.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who, then, were the newly discovered natives? With precious little archaeological or philological evidence to work with, scholars turned to fairy tales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1900 John Rhys, the first Oxford Professor of Celtic, delivered the presidential address to the Anthropology section of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/reportofbritisha00scie&quot;&gt;British Association for the Advancement of Science&lt;/a&gt;. His chosen theme was the value of folk tales for the study of the ancient past, and he argued that behind the ‘rabble of divinities and demons’ who disport themselves in Celtic folklore it is possible to discern the succession of peoples who have inhabited the British Isles. Welsh fairy stories, according to Rhys, contained dim memories of the native population encountered by the first Celtic-speaking intruders. The real ‘little people’, he inferred, had been ‘a small swarthy population of mound-dwellers, of an unwarlike disposition… and living underground’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Cook4.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cook4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Picture from the cover of &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/watcherbythresho00buchuoft&quot;&gt;John Buchan’s The Watcher by the Threshold&lt;/a&gt; (London, 1902).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rhys’ ideas seem to have sparked the imagination of a couple of young minds. John Buchan went up to Oxford in 1895. His short story ‘No-Man’s-Land’, which appeared in print seven years later, tells the dreadful story of an Oxford scholar of Northern Antiquities (like Rhys perhaps, or one of his students), who holidays in the remote Highlands of Scotland, where he encounters – and is  taken captive by – ‘the Hidden People’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then suddenly in the hollow trough of mist before me… there appeared a figure. It was little and squat and dark; naked, apparently, but so rough with hair that it wore the appearance of a skin-covering… in its face and eyes there seemed to lurk an elder world of mystery and barbarism, a troll-like life which was too horrible for words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While captive in their ‘hill refuge’ the Oxford scholar hears harsh words directed at the British invader, bitter curses for the Saxon stranger; and he glimpses ‘a morbid hideous existence’ preserved for centuries by these relics of a nameless past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchan’s natives are the complete antithesis of the modern British subject; a sort of primitive Hyde to the modern Dr. Jekyll. One can perhaps discern a post-WWII twist to this fable in &lt;em&gt;The Inheritors&lt;/em&gt;, the 1955 novel by William Golding (who incidentally attended the same Oxford college as Buchan). In Golding’s story the original dwellers of the land have become Neanderthals – a separate species to modern humans. But in contrast to Buchan, Golding represents these natives as a peaceful if queer-thinking folk; it is the human intruders who are violent and frightening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buchan’s portrayal of Britain’s ancient folk as radically different to the modern population of the British Isles made for a good story; but it did not reflect an Edwardian scholarly consensus that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; newcomers to Britain had interbred with those already settled on the land. Far from being a separate species, scholars believed that much native blood flows through the veins of the inhabitants of modern Britain (the same kind of idea is now put in terms of DNA). An Englishman, a Scotsman, or a Welshmen who meets one of the forgotten little people is quite possibly discovering but a smaller version of himself. And if such encounters have today become rather rare in the fields and hedgerows of Britain, this is a familiar enough experience to many readers of J.R.R. Tolkien’s classic children’s story of 1937, &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hobbits are a homely depiction of Britain’s natives. Tolkien tells us that they are a ‘little people’, who today ‘have become rare and shy of the Big People, as they call us’. But once upon a time, ‘long ago in the quiet of the world, when there was less noise and more green’, hobbits were ‘numerous and prosperous’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going up to Oxford in 1911, Tolkien as an undergraduate probably attended Rhys’ lectures; later, in a short essay of 1932, we find him engaging carefully with his scholarship. And it seems that Tolkien had read the Professor of Celtic’s 1900 presidential address. At one point in this lecture Rhys discusses certain ‘underground – or partially underground – habitations’ that, he believed, had been home to Britain’s natives. These abodes, he explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;appear from the outside like hillocks covered with grass, so as presumably not to attract attention… But one of the most remarkable things about them is the fact that the cells or apartments into which they are divided are frequently so small that their inmates must have been of very short stature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if Tolkien first stumbled upon a hobbit hole whilst reading Rhys’ lecture, it seems likely that his imagination drew also upon Buchan’s depiction of Britain’s natives as subhuman trolls. Certainly, John Buchan was one of Tolkien’s favourite authors. Of course, Bilbo’s hole under the hill is snug and comfortable; the encounter with a ‘hideous existence’ within a ‘hill refuge’ described by Buchan finds its counterpart, not at Bag End, but in that cave deep within the Misty Mountains into which had wormed his way, long ages ago, ‘a small slimy creature’ called Gollum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: ‘Bag End’, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/cwagner33/16412701584/in/photolist-r1konw-f1vrhZ-r9T7na-gSUGYy-fmydgt-oFniqm-qXCt91-eTWhEj-gQcA7v-dW2JCm-nkC5Az-nnouXK-dW2ydC-dTYvrS-qwwRR-rV3eUY-kwR9Kt-78p8QM-kz4UY4-meQa1g-AYZ1kw-7p1Q5Z-rNagXL-5Dke6x-qJhsWF-2bFs5Y-dBstuz-dBxTow-rXvrG5-o6h9pM-dW2C1A-33BvLu-bxVL-ooUeXN-dMMizo-gcABdA-gcxSvr-rXyuCP-rFbrFe-rPZsi5-rhsYc-5vDr9z-gLP9h9-4aysoZ-qFY2N4-rmbW7C-qX9auA-qXdT6B-qZsMSU-nJM8Qs&quot;&gt;Christopher Wagner&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Command Line</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/the_command_line/"/>
   <updated>2016-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/the_command_line</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Drew Holgate, co-founder of Rounded Globe, begins a series of occasional posts highlighting the significance of Linux, the free software movement, and other techy issues that the educated public should be aware of, but aren’t.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Don’t you have to use the command line?” or “Isn’t Linux a command line?” are concerns people often raise when thinking about switching to Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they tend to be mollified with something like “No, you never need to touch the command line. You can do everything you’d do on any other computer without ever seeing the command line”. Which is perfectly true. But we see the unspoken question in their eyes; “If you don’t have to use it, then why on earth &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; you?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They don’t actually ask it because they’re afraid we’ll talk more about Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s understandable, to their eyes the command line looks archaic — it’s what people used in the 70s and we’ve got &lt;em&gt;graphics&lt;/em&gt; now — why would you use something so &lt;em&gt;crude&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;/images/the_command_line.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/the_command_line.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Well it’s beautiful to &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are using a computer you are communicating with it; you are telling it what you want it to do and it is telling you the results of what you asked. The Linux command line is a verbal language for communicating with your computer. Linux commands are words in a language, each embodying one idea. Like words in any language, they can be arranged into sentences of any length and complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose, for some reason, I wanted an ordered, uppercase list of all the most common words in this document I’m writing now. In English that would be “Produce a list of the thirty most common words in this document with a frequency count, order it by frequency and then alphabetically, convert the words to uppercase and then email me the list”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the language of the Linux command line that would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;tr -d &quot;\&quot;,&quot; &amp;lt; the_command_line.md | tr -cs &quot;[:graph:]&quot; &quot;\n&quot; | tr &quot;[:lower:]&quot; &quot;[:upper:]&quot; | awk &#39;{h[$1]++}END{for (i in h){print i&quot; (&quot;h[i]&quot;)&quot;}}&#39;| sort -nr -t$&#39;(&#39; -k2 -k1d | cat -n | head -n 30 | mailx -s &quot;common words&quot; uo.is.ou@gmail.com
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second later, &lt;a href=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/XCWUT0w.png&quot;&gt;the email arrives&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any verbal language, you need to learn it before you can use it. But, like any language, you start small; first learning syntax and then filling out vocabulary. And of course &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man_page&quot;&gt;there’s a command&lt;/a&gt; for finding out what each command means and how to use it — a combined dictionary and textbook of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could save the above command, perhaps calling it ‘count2email’, and then it becomes a word I can use — I have coined a new word in the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A graphical user interface only allows the user to perform the discrete set of tasks that the programmer has explicitly provided — an application can either do something (like emailing a list of all the commonly used words) or it can’t. The command line allows the user to tell the computer &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what to do. It is precise, expressive and lends itself particularly well to complex or repetitive tasks. If I wanted my computer to, every third Tuesday, make a list of the most common words in the file I have written to most recently, overlay those words on a randomly chosen image of a kitten from the internet and then post that image to my website, I could do that. I don’t know why I’d want to, but I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there are certain tasks for which a graphical interface is better-suited. But for those where it’s not, using one is like trying to have a conversation with another human using only Pictionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why some people use the command line. Not out of necessity, but out of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ken_Thompson_%28sitting%29_and_Dennis_Ritchie_at_PDP-11_%282876612463%29.jpg&quot;&gt;Header image&lt;/a&gt;: Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie, the inventors of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix&quot;&gt;Unix&lt;/a&gt;. CC BY-SA license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Chaucer Goes to the Golden Horde</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/chaucer-goes-to-the-golden-horde/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/chaucer-goes-to-the-golden-horde</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today we publish a post by the historical novelist Bryn Hammond, whose &lt;a href=&quot;http://roundedglobe.com/book/54f6f692a26359d553f3348e/Voices%20from%20the%20Twelfth-Century%20Steppe&quot;&gt;_Voices from the Twelfth-Century Steppe_&lt;/a&gt; is scheduled for publication by Rounded Globe on March 15, 2016.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration smallimg left&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;http://amgalant.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/800px-Diego-homem-black-sea-ancient-map-1559.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://amgalant.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/800px-Diego-homem-black-sea-ancient-map-1559.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Black Sea map 1559. Wiki Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaucer set his &lt;em&gt;Squire’s Tale&lt;/em&gt; at ‘Sarray, in the land of Tartarye’ – that is, Saray, city of the Golden Horde Mongols, Jochi’s &lt;em&gt;ulus&lt;/em&gt;, above the Black and Caspian Seas. What did Chaucer know or care about a Tartar khan at Saray and his court?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Squire’s Tale&lt;/em&gt;, as a romance, has been despised in the past; people have said it’s unfinished either because Chaucer had too much discrimination to go on or because the other Canterbury pilgrims stopped the squire’s drivel. You can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.librarius.com/cantales.htm&quot;&gt;read it yourself&lt;/a&gt; and judge. If you like medieval romances (adventure tales, with fantastic happenings, errant knights and wandering plots), there’s nothing wrong with it. It is unfinished, to the point that it’s only just begun. We are left with the khan’s daughter, gifted with a ‘quaint ring’ that lets her understand the talk of birds, having listened to the confession of a she-falcon, intent on self-harm, who has been seduced and left for a rival; the rest of the court are still asleep, after a grand feast whereat was given to the khan a flying horse of brass, that transports you anywhere when you tweak its ears. Nobody knows what happened next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration smallimg right&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;http://amgalant.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/1024px-Flying_Horse_East_Han_Dynasty.Bronze._Gansu_Provincial_Museum.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://amgalant.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/1024px-Flying_Horse_East_Han_Dynasty.Bronze._Gansu_Provincial_Museum.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Flying Horse (hoof on a swallow), East Han Dynasty, bronze. Wiki Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be dismissed as a mishmash of wild marvels ‘for those who like that sort of thing’. Who knew that the &lt;em&gt;Squire’s Tale&lt;/em&gt; had historical value? Carmel Jordan told the world in 1987 when she consulted archaeological work written in Russian, and saw that the Golden Horde was as spectacular as Chaucer describes (you can take &lt;a href=&quot;http://ibnbattuta.berkeley.edu/6goldenhorde.html&quot;&gt;a little trip&lt;/a&gt; with Ibn Battuta, to visit the khan in his gold-tiled tent in 1332-3). The setting, at least, wasn’t wild imagination; and furthermore, she suggests that every marvel had its real-life kick-off: the bronze horse, for instance, might have been put into Chaucer’s head by gift steeds that caused a stir at Mongol courts for their unusual size and general foreign glamour. The khans had a fascination with contrivances, too, that might inspire Chaucer’s magical ornamentation: the ingenious silver tree that dispensed drinks at Karakorum had its counterpart in Saray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration smallimg left&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;http://amgalant.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/Castiglione-Horse_Chaonier.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://amgalant.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/Castiglione-Horse_Chaonier.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Giuseppe Castiglione (1688-1766), court painter for the Qing, one of his Four Afghan Steeds. Wiki Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaucer, unfortunately, never set foot in Saray himself or indeed the Golden Horde. How did he come to be informed? In the latter 13th and the 14th centuries, near the end of which the &lt;em&gt;Squire’s Tale&lt;/em&gt; was written, the khans of Saray and the Italian merchant republics operated in a symbiosis, for an unprecedented age of trade. Genoese, above Venetians, won the major part of the Black Sea trade, and moved with confidence in the Mongol world. Genoa also outstripped other Italian cities in trade relations with England. Chaucer took part in a delegation to Genoa for trade discussions in 1372-3; subsequently he was employed in Customs for the port of London. It is agreed he had ample opportunity, in diplomatic and commercial circles, to hear from Genoese their tales of Saray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently Michael Murrin has written a great book on &lt;em&gt;Trade and Romance&lt;/em&gt;: how romance, first turned by Marco Polo’s travels, changed from a ‘Celtic fantastic’ to a ‘marvelous real’ – set in Asia, and driven not by the interests of aristocratic fighting men, although these remain the heroes of romance, but by the adventurous activities of merchants. He posits a dual audience for such romances as the Squire’s Tale, both upper class and those who live by commerce. It is the case that fighting men didn’t visit Saray: merchants did (not that these merchants weren’t up for a fight). Merchants went further, and saw things undreamt of by knights. The popular romances followed in their steps – but doing this, they lost status, and were trivialised, too, in the scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;illustration&quot;&gt;


&lt;a href=&quot;http://amgalant.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/Braun_Genova_UBHD-View-of-Genoa-in-1572.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://amgalant.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/Braun_Genova_UBHD-View-of-Genoa-in-1572.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;View of Genoa 1572. Wiki Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m fascinated by Chaucer’s trip of the imagination to Saray, and later adventures too of European romancers in the Mongol world. More to come on my own blog, &lt;a href=&quot;http://amgalant.com/&quot;&gt;Amgalant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-works-consulted&quot;&gt;Main works consulted:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virgil Ciocîltan, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brill.com/mongols-and-black-sea-trade-thirteenth-and-fourteenth-centuries&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Mongols and the Black Sea Trade in the Thirteenth and Fourteenth Centuries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, translated by Samuel Willcocks, Leiden, Brill, 2012.   &lt;br /&gt;
Carmel Jordan, ‘Soviet Archeology and the Setting of the Squire’s Tale’, &lt;em&gt;The Chaucer Review&lt;/em&gt;, volume 22, issue 2, 1987, pp. 128-9.  &lt;br /&gt;
Michael Murrin, &lt;a href=&quot;http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/T/bo16552205.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trade and Romance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Chicago &amp;amp; London, University of Chicago Press, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header image: Caravan of Marco Polo, from the Catalan Atlas 1375, attr. to Cresques Abraham. Wiki Commons.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Grand Challenges for Archaeology</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/grand-challenges-for-archaeology/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/grand-challenges-for-archaeology</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Michael E. Smith’s post is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dougsarchaeology.wordpress.com/2016/01/01/the-grand-challenges-for-archaeology-a-blogging-carnival/&quot;&gt;Grand challenges for archaeology blogging carnival&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do archaeology in order to learn about the past. This is a pretty broad purview. We learn about an amazing variety of past things from archaeology, from Richard III’s posture to the causes of the Maya collapse, from what the Natufians ate for breakfast to how the Plains peoples hunted bison. We work hard to recover treasure, garbage, dirt, tools, cathedrals and latrines, and we use them to make statements about what happened long ago. We ask all sorts of questions: Whodunnit? What the heck is that? Why is this particular coin sitting in that specific layer? What were they thinking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do archaeology for many diverse purposes, from reconstructing the lives of ancient kings and queens to creating historical narratives, from helping communities reconstruct their past to complying with government regulations. In this essay I will discuss one of those purposes—creating reliable information about past human societies. This is the primary goal of the archaeology I do, and to my mind this is the most important contribution archaeology makes to human knowledge. Another way of saying this is to claim that archaeology is a social science (Smith et al. 2012). That is, we contribute to the stock of knowledge about human societies around the globe and into the past. Our special brand of knowledge is distinctive in several ways that most of us can rattle off easily. We have access to human societies not documented by any other discipline (e.g., Natufian society). We can study change over longer periods of time than can historians. And we learn about aspects of past societies that cannot be studied well by other fields (e.g., material culture).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade I have become involved in several transdisciplinary research projects. I have learned to interact with scholars in other disciplines (including geography, planning, sociology, political science, economics, and physics), and I have had to read widely in disciplines far outside my comfort zone of archaeology and anthropology. These experiences have made me simultaneously optimistic and pessimistic about the ability of archaeology to generate reliable information about past human societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My optimism has several components. First, our findings really do stand out as unique and important in bringing to light societies not accessible in any other way. I take examples from comparative urbanism, one of my research foci. Archaeology now describes quite a few fascinating and unique past cities and urban traditions—huge dense Tripolyan settlements (urban or not? How did so many Neolithic people live together?); the low-density urbanism of Mesoamerica, Africa and Asia (how did these cities work in a jungle setting?); or Çatalhöyük. Second, archaeology really does produce unique and important data—even on “historical” societies. No other discipline can study past settlement patterns, and archaeology has an incredible record of data on settlement sizes in many past regions. Third, a growing number of scholars in other disciplines actually take archaeological findings seriously and want to engage with archaeologists to learn more and to use our data. I am still surprised at this situation. Prior to going interdisciplinary ten years ago, my colleagues in cultural anthropology rarely expressed any interest at all in archaeology or my research. Now I interact with scholars in different disciplines who think our data can contribute to their research agendas. Amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am also depressingly pessimistic about whether archaeological data can really contribute to social science knowledge and research beyond a couple of small projects here and there. Another way of putting this is to say that I think it will be hard to respond adequately to the many “grand challenges” to archaeology identified by Kintigh et al. (2014a, 2014b) until this higher-order challenge is pursued (click &lt;a href=&quot;http://publishingarchaeology.blogspot.co.il/2014/01/the-grand-challenges-for-archaeology.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for my take on those earlier grand challenges). This is my grand challenge here—to make the effort to change many entrenched archaeological practices to allow us to create reliable knowledge about past societies. We do good fieldwork, and our methods are constantly improving. We have access to a growing suite of sophisticated analytical techniques. But the results of our fieldwork and analysis are not yet building a solid foundation of evidence and data about past societies. Why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;two major roadblocks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our data are not available; and,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our epistemology is inadequate, particularly in the areas of theory and argument.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-data-are-not-available&quot;&gt;(1) Our data are not available&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “gray literature” of unpublished and poorly available contract archaeology reports is a vast sink of archaeological data. Some of it is reported in formats that can be used by other scholars, and some is not. Some is posted online, much is not. There is more contract archaeology going on around the world than grant-funded academic research, yet most of the results contribute little or nothing to building a systematic foundation of knowledge about the past. This needs to change. There are far too many academic archaeological research projects that are never adequately published, leaving important artifacts moldering in a dusty lab or analyzed data locked up in individual idiosyncratic data formats. And even archaeological data from projects that are published can be difficult to access; we need datafiles—not printed tables of numbers—and more excavation photographs—not the few that made it into the report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is getting uncomfortably personal now. My current project will be published and the data archived on tDAR before too long (I hope!). But the primary data for my earlier projects are sitting in ring binders, negative holders, a bunch of Excel and Access databases, and my own head. Should I start another fieldwork project, or spend my time archiving old data? The former is more fun, but perhaps the latter is of greater value to the discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge here is to change the behavior of individuals (like me) and to promote institutional solutions that will make our data available. Even when data ARE available, they will often need cleaning and sorting and recoding if we are going to compare our data to social science data about the present (Smith 2010). Creating and using data archives is a big part of this challenge, and that is why &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tdar.org/about/&quot;&gt;archives like tDAR&lt;/a&gt; are so important. But a change in the culture of archaeology may also be required. When an economic historian publishes a study that uses quantitative data, the datafiles are regularly posted and made available for others to use and reanalyze. Could anyone reanalyze my data that way? Not yet. We don’t have a culture within archaeology that promotes the easy sharing of data. A change in these norms would be a big improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-epistemology-is-inadequate&quot;&gt;(2) Our epistemology is inadequate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Archaeology is a science, in the standard social-science conception of science as having these traits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge is responsive to evidence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Claims are exposed to challenge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Findings should be internally coherent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arguments should be judged on the basis of explanatory power, generality, simplicity, and replicability. For discussion of these traits, see: Gerring (2012) or Wylie (2000).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of my colleagues who view archaeology as a branch of the humanities, or who are hostile to science for reasons postmodern or other, please ignore the following discussion; it does not apply to you. But if one accepts the notion that archaeology does indeed (or can) conform to the model of science as outline above, then one has to be depressed about the current state of archaeological epistemology. Propositions are rarely tested, claims are too infrequently challenged, and formal arguments are rarely examined for adequacy. I explore this situation and provide suggestions for improving our arguments in Smith (2015). One result of our sloppy epistemology is that we have failed to create a solid body of empirical knowledge that can be improved, refined, and extended as research proceeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When postmodernism hit the social sciences in the 1980s, disciplines such as sociology and political science gave it a look, made a few changes, and got back to work. But in anthropology or archaeology, postmodernism settled in as a systemic infection and pushed empirical, scientific approaches to the margins. In the archaeology of complex societies, postmodernism is still festering (post-processualism, post-structuralism, post-humanism, etc.). The assumptions of postmodern approaches contradict the principles of science as listed above. Postmodern approaches are incapable of testing empirical propositions or carrying out rigorous comparative analysis. This is not just my peculiar view of the world; this is basic social science epistemology, discussed in a rather extensive literature rarely considered by archaeologists (6 and Bellamy 2012; Gerring 2012; Hedström 2005; Mjøset 2001; Tilly 1994, 2008).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although few archaeologists use the phrase “postmodern” these days, this anti-science perspective is rampant in the discipline. As noted by a noted postmodern geographer, scholars now prefer to use the term “post-structuralism” because it is a “safer sounding label” than postmodernism (Soja 2001:11863). A major goal of scholarship from this perspective is to deconstruct or problematize knowledge. That is, the idea is to break down established knowledge. In science, on the other hand, the goal is to build and extend reliable bodies of knowledge. In several blog posts—see &lt;a href=&quot;http://publishingarchaeology.blogspot.co.il/2012/01/rejected-by-science_27.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://publishingarchaeology.blogspot.co.il/2012/06/science-type-1-vs-science-type-2.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;—I have discussed two types of “science” in archaeology. Science type 1 is research with a scientific epistemology as discussed here. Science type 2 is work in an interpretivist or non-scientific framework that employs scientific techniques from other disciplines as part of the research process. Archaeologists pursing this model can sometimes fool scientific granting agencies by touting their use of archaeometry or “archaeological science,” while hiding the fact that their research is governed by a non-scientific epistemology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only research carried out with a scientific epistemology, making rigorous empirical arguments about data and about the past, serves to build a body of archaeological knowledge that is capable of generating reliable conclusions about past human societies (beyond descriptions of individual sites or finds). The prevalence of non-scientific epistemologies in archaeology (all the “post-“ approaches) makes it difficult to create this reliable knowledge. Yet for many of us, the goal of our work is to say something useful about past human societies. As in the case of the first roadblock—data availability—the promotion of a scientific epistemology will require a change in the culture of archaeology. If we want to contribute to a body of empirical evidence about human societies and their change over time, then we have our work cut out for us. If we fail to meet this “grand challenge,” then it is hard to see how we can meet all the other grand challenges identified by Kintigh et al. (2014a, 2014b) and by the other bloggers participating in this event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6, Perri and Christine Bellamy. 2012. &lt;em&gt;Principles of Methodology: Research Design in Social Science&lt;/em&gt;. Sage, New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerring, John. 2012. &lt;em&gt;Social Science Methodology: A Unified Framework&lt;/em&gt;. 2nd ed. Cambridge University Press, New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedström, Peter. 2005. &lt;em&gt;Dissecting the Social: On the Principles of Analytical Sociology&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge University Press, New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kintigh, Keith W., Jeffrey Altschul, Mary Beaudry, Robert Drennan, Ann Kinzig, Timothy Kohler, W. Frederick Limp, Herbert Maschner, William Michener, Timothy Pauketat, Peter Peregrine, Jeremy Sabloff, Tony Wilkinson, Henry Wright, and Melinda Zeder. 2014. ‘Grand Challenges for Archaeology’. &lt;em&gt;American Antiquity&lt;/em&gt; 79 (1): 5-24.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kintigh, Keith W., Jeffrey H. Altschul, Mary C. Beaudry, Robert D. Drennan, Ann P. Kinzig, Timothy A. Kohler, W. Frederick Limp, Herbert D. G. Maschner, William K. Michener, Timothy R. Pauketat, Peter Peregrine, Jeremy A. Sabloff, Tony J. Wilkinson, Henry T. Wright, and Melinda A. Zeder. 2014. ‘Grand Challenges for Archaeology’. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 122: 879-880.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mjøset, Lars. 2001. ‘Theory: Conceptions in the Social Sciences’. In &lt;em&gt;International Encyclopedia of the Social and Behavioral Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Neil J. Smelser and Paul B. Baltes, pp. 15641-15647. Elsevier, New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smith, Michael E. 2010. ‘Sprawl, Squatters, and Sustainable Cities: Can Archaeological Data Shed Light on Modern Urban Issues?’ &lt;em&gt;Cambridge Archaeological Journal&lt;/em&gt; 20: 229-253.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smith, Michael E. 2015. ‘How can Archaeologists Make Better Arguments?’ &lt;em&gt;The SAA Archaeological Record&lt;/em&gt; 15 (4): 18-23.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smith, Michael E., Gary M. Feinman, Robert D. Drennan, Timothy Earle, and Ian Morris. 2012. ‘Archaeology as a Social Science’. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 109: 7617-7621.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soja, Edward W. 2001. ‘Postmodernism in Geography’. In &lt;em&gt;International Encyclopedia of the Social and Behavioral Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Neil J. Smelser and Paul B. Baltes, pp. 11860-11865. Elsevier, New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tilly, Charles. 1994. ‘Softcore Solipsism’. &lt;em&gt;Labour / Le Travail&lt;/em&gt; 34: 259-268.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tilly, Charles. 2008. &lt;em&gt;Explaining Social Processes&lt;/em&gt;. Paradigm Publishers, Boulder, CO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wylie, Alison. 2000. ‘Questions of Evidence, Legitimacy, and the (Dis)unity of Science’. &lt;em&gt;American Antiquity&lt;/em&gt; 65: 227-237.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image credit: ‘Aztec Ruins NM’, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/jb10okiefwpp/&quot;&gt;jb10okie&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Origins of British Agriculture</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/origins-of-british-agriculture/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/origins-of-british-agriculture</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The first of a series of posts by Dr Mark McKerracher on the origins of agriculture. Subsequent posts will be published in this blog from time to time…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A relative of mine asked me how agriculture came about in the first place. It’s a fair enough question. We’re all so familiar with the concept of farming, that it’s hardly obvious how our distant ancestors moved from hunting and gathering to tilling the hateful earth. Indeed, I don’t (yet) have an answer to my relative’s question, but I thought I should start putting one together. And to avoid anything so strenuous as making a plan, I’ve decided to write these “Origins” in the order that things come to my attention, rather than the order in which they happened… not least because the chronology of early farming might prove to be a little tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, what better place to start than Britain itself, home to this blogger, and subject to a recent article in that venerable warhorse &lt;em&gt;Antiquity&lt;/em&gt; (Stevens &amp;amp; Fuller 2012). This article begins by claiming to rewrite the early history of Britain – no small claim! And as a bonus (for me), it’s written by two archaeobotanists, so how could I resist reviewing it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, it’s worth stating at the outset that we’re talking here about the Neolithic – the ‘new’ stone age, between about 6,000 and 4,000 years ago, a period which is broadly characterized by the widespread adoption of both farming and, increasingly, sedentary settlements. So how did this major change occur, and how quickly? As Stevens &amp;amp; Fuller describe, previous scholarship can be roughly divided into ‘abrupt’ and ‘gradual’ models. In the former case, the Neolithic starts with an agricultural bang; in the latter, agriculture is gradually adopted more and more from the later Mesolithic, through the Neolithic, and into the Bronze Age (pp.707-8). So what happened in Britain? And how on earth can we find out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stevens &amp;amp; Fuller’s favoured approach is thoroughly &lt;em&gt;archaeobotanical&lt;/em&gt;: that is, they study the remains of ancient plants – specifically, the charred remains of cultivated and wild food plants. Fortunately, organic remains such as these can often be radiocarbon-dated, and the authors have compiled an impressive database with hundreds of dated items from Mesolithic, Neolithic and Bronze Age excavations in Britain. Basically, they chart the occurrence of crops (especially cereals) over time, and compare it to that of wild food plants (especially hazelnuts, which survive in particular abundance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, they find some intriguing patterns. Firstly, Britain’s first domesticated crops seem to appear pretty early in the Neolithic, soon after 4,000 BC, with a relatively rapid uptake across the British Isles. Secondly, however, the occurrence of crops – relative to wild food plants – apparently tails off around 3,300 BC. In other words, their database has few if any dated crop remains for the ‘Middle’ and ‘Late Neolithic’, while hazelnuts continue to occur throughout these periods. Cereals don’t make a comeback until the Middle Bronze Age (around 1,500 BC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stevens &amp;amp; Fuller therefore conclude that cereal-farming, although introduced in the Early Neolithic, was then abandoned during the millennia that witnessed the construction of monuments including Stonehenge. Only in the Middle Bronze Age did cereal-farming really set in for good. The  abandonment coincides broadly with some other perceived archaeological patterns: population decline and monument construction (including Stonehenge). By way of explanation, the authors suggest that &lt;em&gt;climatic deterioration&lt;/em&gt;, causing a run of bad harvests, may have led to the abandonment of early cereal-cultivation. But palaeoclimatology can be a rather slippery subject so, as usual, I’ll tip-toe carefully around it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a prehistorian, so I don’t feel qualified to comment too specifically on this paper. But I did find it fascinating. A relatively simple methodology (collecting figures and tracing patterns) has shown intriguing, unexpected results. This aspect particularly appeals to me, because it’s not unlike my own research. Archaeobotany so often languishes in specialist appendices of site reports with little attention to its (potentially very great) significance, so it’s pleasing to see plant remains taking centre stage in this article. But as the authors stress in their conclusion, the result is a very broad picture – broad in terms of geography and chronology – and of course it’s possible that the overall patterns may change considerably as more data become available. Even so, perhaps my favourite conclusion is this one (p.720):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…the paper demonstrates the limitations of using traditional period divisions and highlights the need to escape the tyranny of the ‘Neolithic’ label, and its assumption of unchanging village farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good point well made. I like period divisions as much as the next archaeologist – but we shouldn’t let them get the upper hand! Food for thought indeed…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MJM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stevens, C. &amp;amp; Fuller, D. (2012). ‘Did Neolithic farming fail? The case for a Bronze Age agricultural revolution in the British Isles’, &lt;em&gt;Antiquity&lt;/em&gt; 86, 707-722.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image credit: ‘Stonehenge’, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/ianan/4909120122/in/photolist-8tNwo7-fpPF42-9XAHSk-8YhAZo-dMd56j-dM7up2-9DpsQM-6ZVLm4-pmC8dg-3qseBd-4zbFfQ-nLnqdz-6igADe-4p5dAH-68NM4k-aaNBCk-dZ21Bu-obn5TU-jHGKT5-fq4X1w-5immPU-xJHgBa-63Eu64-6yao4i-8Ukdtd-pmkXAP-7UftvE-5u9Vfd-8cb1Ya-jHHsno-aZ7hGt-aZ7hm2-jHHAPJ-jHEydM-3qnQtD-aZ7hbP-aZ7gw2-fpC2FA-aZ7ffi-aZ7f6i-aZ7fSX-aZ7gbP-8Ukc4E-j7d4MR-6yBdaS-uTXcur-dxVdYM-5VhP5Y-bvswrs-fGAr81&quot;&gt;Ianan&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Can&#39;t Disrupt This</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/can't-disrupt-this/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/can't-disrupt-this</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;elsevier-and-the-252-billion-dollar-a-year-academic-publishing-business&quot;&gt;# Elsevier and the 25.2 Billion Dollar A Year Academic Publishing Business&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scribd.com/doc/292346391/Forbes-Elsevier-1995&quot;&gt;December 18, 1995&lt;/a&gt;), Forbes predicted academic publisher Elsevier’s relevancy and life in the digital age to be short lived. In an article entitled “The internet’s first victim,” journalist John Hayes highlights the technological imperative coming toward the academic publisher’s profit margin with the growing internet culture and said, “Cost-cutting librarians and computer-literate professors are bypassing academic journals — bad news for Elsevier.” After publication of the article, investors seemed to heed Hayes’s rationale for Elsevier’s impeding demise. Elsevier stock fell 7% in two days to $26 a share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the smoke settles twenty years later, one of the clear winners on this longitudinal timeline of innovation is the very firm that investors, journalists, and forecasters wrote off early as a casualty to digital evolution: Elsevier. Perhaps to the chagrin of many academics, the publisher has actually not been bruised nor battered. In fact, the publisher’s health is stronger than ever. As of 2015, the academic publishing market that Elsevier leads has an annual revenue of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stm-assoc.org/2015_02_20_STM_Report_2015.pdf&quot;&gt;$25.2 billion&lt;/a&gt;. According to its 2013 financials &lt;a href=&quot;http://poeticeconomics.blogspot.co.il/2014/03/elsevier-stm-publishing-profits-rise-to.html&quot;&gt;Elsevier&lt;/a&gt; had a higher percentage of profit than &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2013/10/28Apple-Reports-Fourth-Quarter-Results.html&quot;&gt;Apple, Inc.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Schmitt1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Nosek, a professor at the University of Virginia and director of the Center for Open Science, says, “Academic publishing is the perfect business model to make a lot of money. You have the producer and consumer as the same person: the researcher. And the researcher has no idea how much anything costs.” Nosek finds this whole system is designed to maximize the amount of profit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I, as the researcher, produce the scholarship and I want it to have the biggest impact possible and so what I care about is the prestige of the journal and how many people read it. Once it is finally accepted, since it is so hard to get acceptances, I am so delighted that I will sign anything — send me a form and I will sign it. I have no idea I have signed over my copyright or what implications that has — nor do I care, because it has no impact on me. The reward is the publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nosek further explains why researchers are ever supportive by explaining the dedicated loyal customer base mantra, “What do you mean libraries are canceling subscriptions to this? I need this. Are you trying to undermine my research?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to a steadfast dedication by researchers, the academic publishing market, in its own right, is streamlined, aggressive, and significantly capitalistic. The publishing market is also more diverse than just the face of Elsevier. Johan Rooryck, a professor at Universiteit Leiden, says, “Although Elsevier is the publisher that everybody likes to hate, if you look at Taylor &amp;amp; Francis, Wiley, or Springer they all have the same kind of practices.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heather Morrison, a professor in the School of Information Studies at the University of Ottawa, unpacks the business model behind academic publisher Springer and says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you look at who owns Springer, these are private equity firms, and they have changed owners about five times in the last decade. Springer was owned by the investment group Candover and Cinven who describe themselves as ‘Europe’s largest buy-out firm.’ These are companies who buy companies to decrease the cost and increase the profits and sell them again in two years. This is to whom we scholars are voluntarily handing our work. Are you going to trust them? This is not the public library of science. This is not your average author voluntarily contributing to the commons. These are people who are in business to make the most profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should a consumer heed Morrison’s rationale and want to look deeper into academic publishers cost structure for themselves one is met with a unique situation: the pricing lists for journals do not exist. “It’s because they negotiate individually with each institution and they often have non-disclosure agreements with those institutions so they can’t bargain with knowing what others paid,” says Martin Eve, founder of the Open Library of the Humanities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to a general lack of pricing indexes, the conversation around the value of a publication is further complicated by long-term career worth. David Sundahl, a senior research fellow at the Clayton Christensen Institute for Disruptive Innovation, says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We actually understand how money passed through to artists who wrote music and authors who wrote books — but it is not clear how the value of a publication in a top tier journal will impact someone’s career. Unlike songs or books where the royalty structure is defined, writing a journal article is not clear and is dependent not on the people who consume the information but rather deans and tenure committees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Schmitt2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disruption-doable&quot;&gt;Disruption Doable?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is precisely the prior lack of a pricing and value barometer that leads to the complexities associated with disrupting the main players in academic publishing. “Adam Smith’s invisible hand works to lower prices and increase productivity but it can only do so when valuation or pricing is known and the same thing is true for disruption. If you don’t know how to value something, you actually don’t have tiers of a market,” says Sundahl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a disruptive force was to significantly change academic publishing it needs to happen in a market that is currently underserved or undesirable by the large-scale publisher. “Disruptive innovation is usually driven by a group who can’t afford to build something that is as big, fancy and sophisticated as the existing solution — they then have to find a market where either people don’t have anything available to them or they are satisfied with something less than perfect,” says Sundahl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should academic scholarship keep existing in a similar trajectory as in the past decades Sundahl finds incumbents (existing big publishers) almost always win when competition takes place along those sustaining strategy lines. “To revolutionize academic publication, a new system would need to be developed in a basement market which would eventually enable people to gain enough credibility doing this new solution. People would then begin to value this lower end, well done research, and that is when the world starts to change,” says Sundahl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prior is exactly what large entities like the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation or perhaps even top tier research one (R1) universities can’t do. “They have to play the game the way the winners are already playing it. Incumbents almost always win under those conditions,” says Sundahl. And to further complicate matters, junior colleges and community colleges, which perhaps would represent fertile grounds to be served by a newer, “basement market” entrant, may be less likely to spearhead this new outlet themselves due increasing government constraints focused nearly exclusively on job placement and starting salaries in lieu of a research-based, theoretical curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-access-packs-a-punch&quot;&gt;Open Access Packs a Punch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driven by the lopsided power structure the move toward open access and the unrestricted access to academic information has been exponentially growing. Perhaps it is, itself, a “basement market” for leveling the academic publication environment and creating a market where respect and credibility can be fostered, grown and transitioned into the existing academic prestige, merit, and tenure conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The open access environment is one of the more fertile environments for people to be thinking: if we don’t like the old way, what should the new way look like,” says Heather Joseph, executive director at the Scholarly Publishing and Academic Resources Coalition (SPARC). Joseph finds that the quantifiable numbers of open access journals speak for themselves and says, “You can look at the number of strictly open access journals if you look at the Directory of Open Access Journals (DOAJ). When it started tracking open access journals there were a few dozen and now they list over 10,000 open access journals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The push toward open access is not only growing in sheer numbers of journals but also in an increasingly confrontational strategy that academics leverage against large publishers. “At the moment, the Netherlands, the whole country, has said to Elsevier that we want all of our researchers to be able to publish open access in your journals at the same rates we would pay for a subscription last year and if you can’t do that we’re going to cancel every one of your journals, for all of our universities nationwide,” says Eve. “They have a few days left to resolve this, and it looks like they are going to cancel all the Elsevier journals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rooryck found his recent very public decision to step down and move his Elsevier journal Linga to open access met with complete support from the other six editors and 31 editorial board members. “The process went very easily. We were all aware of the pricing and Elsevier’s practices and within a week everyone agreed to resign,” says Rooryck. Eve’s platform, the Open Library of Humanities, will now house the new open access iteration of Lingua, which will be called Glossa. Eve says, “Right away it is 50% cheaper to run it through us then when it was with Elsevier. So anybody subscribing to it already sees 50% more revenue.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rooryck finds the move toward broad open access a natural progression and says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The knowledge we produce as academics and scientists should be publicly available in the same way we have a company that delivers water to our faucets and electricity to our home. These are things we have a right to. Public knowledge and education is a human right and it should not come with a profit tag of 35%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it appears open access has the ability to simultaneously diffuse academic knowledge to a larger body of readers and cut costs significantly, many feel that the for profit academic publishers are still situated to continue into the near future. Joseph says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think the play for most smart commercial publishers is to try to preserve the current environment for as long as they can: delay the policy changes, delay the culture changes and to be working on things like tools and services applying to aggregation of data, where they are then embedding themselves more deeply in the workflow of researchers and becoming essential to researchers in a different way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you are no longer essential to researchers in the, ‘you have to publish in my journal in order to get tenure and promotion’ what do they replace that with? I think the smart publishing companies like Elsevier, like Springer, who are very smart in that regard, have been thinking about where they can go to be playing a role of continuing to be seen as essential by the research community once they are no longer playing the role of providing assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;onward-and-upward&quot;&gt;Onward and Upward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the US Congress we have been finally making &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.sciencemag.org/policy/2015/07/senate-panel-approves-public-access-bill&quot;&gt;progress&lt;/a&gt; with the Fair Access to Science and Technology Research (FASTR) bill. It moved through the committee it was referred to in the Senate and is poised to move out of the Senate and potentially be considered by the House and hopefully pass. Ten years ago, I would have said we didn’t have a chance to do a stand-alone bill,” says Joseph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the recent congressional support Joseph refers to is one more verifying measure that the majority of articles will be moving toward an open and accessible framework. Many in the academic community hope that this government support signals the reprioritization of a research framework and the switching of the guard. And while the prior is extremely important, others in the academic community are hoping to grow “basement markets” from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Center for Open Science, which provides seed funds to startups in the academic scientific research space, is led by Nosek and focuses on aligning scientific values to scientific practices. “The open science framework is just a means at connecting all the research services that researchers use across the entire research life cycle,” says Nosek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nosek is optimistic about the evolution of technology in open science and says, “There are a lot of startups going at different parts of the research life cycle. Whether it is publication and what a publication means, or looking at full articles and whether you can make articles convey information in smaller bite size pieces.” Nosek tells me that there are so many solutions happening in research right now and mentions it is hard to judge what the true solutions will look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I sometimes think some of the ideas haven’t a chance, but what do I know? I could be completely wrong about it. And that is the whole point — do some experimentation and try out ideas. And the fact is there are a lot of people who see what the problems are and have a unique sense of a potential solution — it is a very lively time to try out different answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time will tell if open access will be the needed disruption to allow the academic environment to right itself or if a new market emerges from startup incubators like the Center for Open Science. Regardless of how the future vision is realized, most in the academic community hope that the new iteration of scholarly articles and publishing will do more good toward humankind than that of a hefty profit margin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image header credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Book_burning_%283%29.jpg&quot;&gt;Alan Levine&lt;/a&gt;; creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A View from Jerusalem</title>
   <link href="http://roundedglobe.github.io/a-view-from-Jerusalem/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://roundedglobe.github.io/a-view-from-Jerusalem</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Welcome to the Rounded Globe blog! Our first post is an abridged version of Prof. Guy Stroumsa’s closing remarks at a conference held in Jerusalem earlier this month (January 2016). A scholar of comparative religion, Professor Stroumsa discussed the duty of scholarly subsversion. Speaking from the heart of a conflict, Stroumsa calls on intellectuals to step beyond aseptic seminar rooms into the wider world around them: a call to which we at Rounded Globe are deeply sympathetic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, a &lt;em&gt;révolutionnaire manqué&lt;/em&gt;, the comparative study of religions and their cohort of dreams of transformations, of patterns of mutations, both within societies and inside the self, has always represented a deeply subversive activity. I wish to offer here a midrashic reflection of sorts on subversion as an intellectual and moral duty: that of refusing to lie on the Procrustean beds prepared for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last half-century, the Hebrew University has been a true home for me, one which I never really left. A &lt;em&gt;witz&lt;/em&gt; describes psychoanalysts as people whose analysis was not quite successful: they were not able to move ahead. &lt;em&gt;Mutatis mutandis&lt;/em&gt;, the same could be said about professors and their education. The very first day of my new life in Israel, in July 1966 (I was eighteen, as old as the country), was also that of my baptismal day as a student at the Hebrew University – more precisely, at its summer Ulpan: the early stages of my interminable struggle with Hebrew. Like other ambitious universities, the Hebrew University has always known that its first, absolute commitment was to the search for truth and to what it entails: critical thought, moral backbone, intellectual freedom. The intellectual audacity expected from universities is worthless without the civic courage to constantly question thought patterns and attitudes current in their own societies, to affirm, clearly and loudly, their autonomy and independence from the bodies and governments funding them. In Rabelais’ lapidary dictum: “Science sans conscience n’est que ruine de l’âme.” This permanent questioning is, precisely, their duty of subversion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, paradoxically, universities are everywhere under threat, asked to ‘be relevant,’ rather than to search for truth, to ‘deliver’ rather than to educate. I say paradoxically, as human societies, despite blatant, shocking inequalities, have never been as affluent as they are today. I cannot analyze this paradox here or even attempt to suggest solutions. I want at least to stress what you all know, that Faculties of Humanities are much more seriously threatened that those of Sciences and vocational schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural sciences have an easier time, I think, in their rebuttal of utilitarian demands, as it is relatively simple for them to show the value of pure research: no applied mathematics or physics without pure mathematics and physics. At least in theory, one can still make an argument about &lt;em&gt;la science pour la science&lt;/em&gt;, as one does about &lt;em&gt;l’art pour l’art&lt;/em&gt;. A similar argument is far less obvious for the humanities. Very soon, one will hear the argument about what the Germans call the &lt;em&gt;kleine Fächer&lt;/em&gt;, the “small fields,” such as, at least in the Israeli context, the paradigmatic Assyriology: too expensive, too few students. And besides, who cares about Assyriology?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem, I fear, is made more complex by the fact that the humanities, the &lt;em&gt;Geisteswissenschaften&lt;/em&gt;, in their wish to be taken seriously, have calqued themselves on the &lt;em&gt;Naturwissenschaften&lt;/em&gt;. They are still doing that, as shown by the latest fad, “digital humanities,” and by the widely spread tendency to value only what can be quantified. I am all for the use of modern technologies in the service of the humanities, but at the moment, the technologies seem to take over the fields rather than serve them. Faculties of Humanities risk forgetting that their task, beyond producing new knowledge, also consists in offering a reflection on knowledge, on its conditions, its limits and its meaning. Such a second-order reflection is essentially subversive, as it questions the natural acceptance of existing conditions for the reproduction of knowledge in society, including in its educational institutions, and in the political system sustaining them. The humanities are deeply unsettling, and therefore, in this age of increasing resistance to questioning, increasingly unfashionable. By historicizing and relativizing all ideas and world-views, they disturb what is held sacred in all quarters. It is, then, by nature that the humanities, more than any other branch of knowledge in the universities, are subversive. I would go further, and argue that it is only by recognizing and embracing the subversive nature of their craft that humanists can avoid the new, deeply threatening &lt;em&gt;trahison des clercs&lt;/em&gt;, to borrow the title of Julien Benda’s famous pamphlet, toward which the market forces of the global village almost inexorably push us all. Almost inexorably, but perhaps not quite: if the historian (even the historian of religion) is no prophet, she or he can never be sure that the claim of subversion will only remain a symbolic gesture of protest, done only for honor’s sake. It may also, perchance, hide the seed of a future rebirth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the modern university is a secular place: no theological presupposition, no religious limitation may regulate the questioning of scientists and scholars alike. This, we must reckon, creates a particular problem for the study of religion, a problem that cannot be easily dismissed, although it often goes unrecognized. Creating secular knowledge about the sacred is by no means an obvious task, even when one deals with societies far away from ours in either time or space. Nor is the study of religion, despite appearances, perceived as a problem only by those who have religious leanings, and who may feel that their world, their values, are under attack, perhaps even desecrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have come to realize over the years, creating secular knowledge about the sacred is also felt as a threat by the secularists, those who feel enlightened, free from the prejudices and fears so characteristic (they think) of religion. The modern, comparative study of religion is a study of humans, not of gods. More precisely, it is the study of humans dealing with the gods. It is, therefore, more akin to anthropology than to theology. While the study of religion cannot protect religion from the secular invasion (indeed, it reflects and often represents this invasion), it also refuses to evacuate religion from the secular world. In its double movement, the study of religion thus antagonizes both the proponents of a religious worldview and those of a secular one, appearing to both as a threat. No surprise, then, if it is deeply unfashionable. At the same time, it is urgently needed, as it stands at the very core of Faculties of Humanities, encapsulating, as it were, the duty of subversion that is theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, after the last Paris terrorist massacres, a dear friend of mine from Berlin expressed her shock at the speed with which French politicians were switching to a warlike vocabulary. The reticence to speak of war is easily understandable, and highly commendable, certainly on the side of Germans, who can afford historical amnesia even less than others. My immediate reaction to her remark, however, was that I had never considered the world I lived in to be a peaceful one. From the Qumran scroll describing the eschatological War between the Sons of Light with the Sons of Darkness and Mani’s &lt;em&gt;Sermon of the Great War&lt;/em&gt; to more recent bouts of religious violence, in Jamestown, Waco, Ayodhya, Bali, Beirut, New York, Ankara or Bamako, war has always been omnipresent. We know, moreover, that not all Sons of Darkness belong to the enemy camp; some also sit in our midst. For me, then, humanism is conceivable only in a world at war; it must be a fighting humanism. In his theses &lt;em&gt;On the concept of history&lt;/em&gt;, written in 1940, Walter Benjamin could say: “the emergency situation in which we live is the rule.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ultimi barbarorum!” Spinoza’s cry of rage and despair, which he inscribed on a placard when hearing of the lynching of his friends, the De Witt brothers, in 1672, might have cost him his life, had not his lodger wisely locked him up in his room. “Ultimi barbarorum!” This cry resonates today in this impossible city, Jerusalem. Before the end of my first year of studies at the Hebrew University started the Six Day War – a war still going on, almost fifty years later. A life of learning and of teaching under such conditions is something difficult to grasp, and quite hard to sustain, as no university can remain an island of reason in a sea of madness, of honesty in a situation of injustice, certainly not when it stands, and quite concretely so, at the very seam between conqueror and conquered. We have tried seriously, students and teachers alike, to keep our labs, our libraries and our seminar rooms aseptic, as it were, to concentrate on what we were doing, isolated from the world looming right outside our window. &lt;em&gt;Wissenschaft als Beruf&lt;/em&gt;: we have done our best to take Max Weber’s injunction seriously. We have played by the rules of democracy, while a whole people was, and still is being kept under military occupation, without civil rights, now for almost half a century – deprived of its freedom by those whose children read about Israel’s Exodus from Egypt and the books of the prophets in the original biblical Hebrew! For many among us, this has been at times intolerably stressful, unbearably painful. At some point, the bow must break. Under some circumstances, it is in the mode of protest that the duty of the scholar must be expressed. Cultivating the humanities in such a climate does not necessarily entail the splendid isolation of a (more or less) air-conditioned ivory tower. It can also express a potent protest, represent, as it were, a subversive activity against the reigning order. I have long been impressed by what Raja Shehadeh, a Palestinian writer from Ramallah, has called &lt;em&gt;şumūd&lt;/em&gt;, a noble way of resisting daily brutality and the constant rape of the soul by stubbornly sticking to one’s beliefs, way of life, and ethos. Insisting on remaining oneself, on keeping high one’s torch of values in front of politicians lending their support to thugs, ‘thugs for God’s sake,’ one might call them, and transmitting this torch to the youth: there is a real element of subversion here, perhaps even, who knows, a powerful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are left here with a theologico-political aporia rooted in the very nature of Zionism. Like all movements of national liberation, Zionism achieved its goals, at best, only very partially. Here, the founders of the Hebrew University were quite lucid, aware from the start of the deep-seated ambiguities of the adventure in which they were taking part. I shall mention here only Yehuda Leon Magnes, the first President of the Hebrew University, Martin Buber, the first President of the Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities, and Gershom Scholem, another President of this Academy. In his magnum opus, a biography of the seventeenth-century false messiah Sabbatai Zevi, first published (in Hebrew) in 1959, Scholem could warn of the explosive mixture of old messianic ideas and modern political ideals. Today, the dialectics of the return to Zion threaten to lead to what is perceived, by too many, as Israel’s ‘manifest destiny’: after the Reconquista of the whole land, the segregation into reserves of the Palestinians, or even their eventual expulsion. The supreme jewel in David’s crown, for them, would be the rebuilding of the Jerusalem Temple and, one imagines, the ensuing restoration of daily blood sacrifices (what else would one do in the Temple?), after a pause of a mere two millenia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is certainly important, and tragically fascinating, to study the sinuous paths through which religious tradition and cultural legacy can - and do - degenerate into such lunacy. This urgent task is that of historians of religion. But it is not our only task, nor is it our most immediate one. If we wish to avoid what might soon lead to nothing less than a conflict of world dimensions, we must also fight the present neo-messianic madness urgently, and furiously. When fair is foul, and foul is fair, civic courage meets intellectual duty, and intellectual courage means civic duty. The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, its Faculty of Humanities, and its students of religion, must be at the front line in this subversive war against the murderous folly threatening our society and our humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text: ‘Concluding Remarks’ to ‘Upholding Scripture, Rejecting Scripture: Strategies of Religious Subversion: a Conference Celebrating the Work of Guy G. Stroumsa’, Hebrew University of Jerusalem and Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities, Jerusalem, 4-5 January 2016; read at the Israel Academy, 5 January 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Header Image: ‘Coexist Jerusalem: Tunnel near Gaza Street, Jerusalem’ by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/zeevveez/2573448048/&quot;&gt;zeevveez&lt;/a&gt;. Creative commons license.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
